<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Torspark</title>
  <subtitle>Custom Software Development &amp; Consultancy</subtitle>
  <id>http://torspark.com</id>
  <link href="http://torspark.com"/>
  <link href="http://torspark.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2015-02-02T22:04:00-06:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Chris Olds</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>5 A/B Testing Questions (and Answers) You Need to Know</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://torspark.com/5-a-b-testing-questions-and-answers-you-need-to-know/"/>
    <id>http://torspark.com/5-a-b-testing-questions-and-answers-you-need-to-know/</id>
    <published>2015-02-02T22:04:00-06:00</published>
    <updated>2015-02-03T01:50:09-06:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Tania Lyerly</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No Textbook required. Not even a Dictionary.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here at Torspark, we are firm believers in asking lots of questions. With that
in mind, here are the most common questions about A/B testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is A/B testing?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What can A/B testing do for your business...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No Textbook required. Not even a Dictionary.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here at Torspark, we are firm believers in asking lots of questions. With that
in mind, here are the most common questions about A/B testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is A/B testing?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What can A/B testing do for your business?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How does A/B testing work?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do you pick the winner of an A/B test?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How long should you run an A/B test?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bonus Question: What do all of those marketing sales-y speak headlines &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt;
mean?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A straightforward bundle of questions to ask, but the &lt;strong&gt;answers are a different
matter&lt;/strong&gt;. The answers tend to be made more complicated than they should be from a
combination of technical terms and sales-y marketing speak. This is why we
decided to answer these questions, minus the dictionary, textbook, or marketing
translator to understand. Here we go!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;1. What is A/B testing?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A/B testing (or split testing) is when you &lt;strong&gt;test two variations&lt;/strong&gt; of something to
see &lt;strong&gt;which performs better&lt;/strong&gt;. Usually you test a new version (B) that you think
could do better against the control version (A). Or if you don’t have a control
version, you could just start testing both alternatives against each other right
away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can test more than two variations as well. A three variation split test
would be known as an A/B/C test. One letter is assigned for each variation, and
you could continue on with four or more variations in this manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;2. What can A/B testing do for your business?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The primary use for A/B testing is to &lt;strong&gt;gather conversion data&lt;/strong&gt;. To understand the
importance of conversion data, let’s talk about data and sales funnels for a
second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have enough data, you can construct the flow of your sales funnel. This
means determining where your traffic is coming from, how many people are
clicking through your website, how many people end up &lt;strong&gt;buying your product&lt;/strong&gt; or
service, and what path they took to get there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, even the best sales funnels leak. Holes in your funnel are &lt;strong&gt;where people
drop off&lt;/strong&gt; at each stage. By seeing the big picture painted by the data, you can
figure out where the leaks are. Once you know where the barriers to conversion
are, you can start to fix them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fix can be anything from better headlines and copy to adding (or removing)
videos. Sometimes it’s even as simple as changing the color of a button. It
really just &lt;strong&gt;depends on your customers&lt;/strong&gt; and what they respond to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where A/B testing comes into play. It is used to test those fixes to
your leaking sales funnel. By A/B testing the fix, you can determine if your fix
&lt;strong&gt;actually works&lt;/strong&gt;. Or if your fix made your sales funnel leak some more. Or if it
didn’t make a difference either way. Some fixes will have a greater improvement
than others, while sometimes you will need a combination of fixes to see an
improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With some trial and error, you can &lt;strong&gt;find the right combination to optimize
conversions&lt;/strong&gt; and minimize leaks in your sales funnel. The right boost to your
conversion rate should &lt;strong&gt;increase your revenue&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you understand the theory for A/B testing, but what does this look like with
some real numbers? Don&amp;rsquo;t worry, you won&amp;rsquo;t need a calculator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Scientific Calculator and Stats Book" src="/img/scientific-calculator.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say you have a business selling some software. Your current conversion
rate is 10%, and your yearly revenue is $500,000. Your business then conducts
several A/B tests to optimize conversions in your sales funnel (without changing
prices). As a result, you were able to increase your total overall conversion
rate by 3%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You new total conversion rate is now 13% (10% original + 3% improvement = 13%).
That extra 3% increase in your total conversion rate represents an additional
$15,000 in &lt;strong&gt;yearly revenue&lt;/strong&gt; for your business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not a bad chunk of change for running a few tests. Especially when you consider
that your business will get this extra $15,000 &lt;em&gt;every year&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if your business was able to continue to optimize your conversions
overtime? So that 3% increase became 5% or 7% as different tests improved
different aspects of your sales funnel. Those percentages will compound (just
like compounding interest rates), and revenue will really increase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;3. How does A/B testing work?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say you want to target the number of people signing up for a free demo on
your website. You are worried you are missing out on conversions because you
think people &lt;em&gt;aren’t noticing&lt;/em&gt; the bland button that blends into the background.
You decide to perform an A/B test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="A/B testing gray button vs orange button" src="/img/ab-test-gray-orange-button.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original button is version “A” and the new bright orange button is version
“B”. Half of your traffic to the website will see version “A” and half will see
version “B”. Some tools will declare the winning version based on the higher
conversion rate after a set amount of time or visitors. They’ll even
automatically apply the changes as soon as they pick a winner. This &lt;strong&gt;is not&lt;/strong&gt; how
you want to declare a test winner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;4. How do you pick the winner of an A/B test?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Excited Kids with Laptop" src="/img/excited-kids.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Declaring a winner sounds simple, but it can get a little tricky because of the
multiple factors: sample size, statistical significance, and getting an &lt;strong&gt;accurate
representation of your business traffic&lt;/strong&gt;. (Wait, don’t grab your textbook yet!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statistical significance is when a statistic is deemed reliable. So a test with
a 95% statistical significance means there is &lt;strong&gt;less than a 5% chance&lt;/strong&gt; that the
results of the test could be due to &lt;em&gt;random chance&lt;/em&gt;. Remember, the higher the
statistical significance percentage, the more you can trust in the results of
your test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To achieve a higher level of statistical significance, you will need to increase
your sample size (the number of people you are testing). You will also need to
increase your sample size the more variations you test. In all honesty, your
sample size can &lt;em&gt;never be too big&lt;/em&gt;. This is where time and money become factors,
which we’ll explore in the next section. But you will need certain minimums to
achieve statistical significance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sample size and statistical significance alone are &lt;strong&gt;not enough&lt;/strong&gt; to declare a
winner when making business decisions. Your test should run long enough for your
sample size to &lt;strong&gt;accurately represent&lt;/strong&gt; your business traffic. These elements
combined together help you decide how long to run the test for and eventually
for declaring the winner and &lt;strong&gt;making the right decision&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;5. How long should you run an A/B test?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The very simple statistical answer is once a test has reached statistical
significance then the test is complete, but that isn’t entirely accurate when
&lt;strong&gt;trying to make an informed decision&lt;/strong&gt;. It is at best a half answer and very
misleading at worst. You want to achieve a combination of a high level of
statistical significance that is indicative of your conversion funnel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider this&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if you get all of the traffic you need for statistical significance in an
hour? Is that one hour’s worth of traffic truly representative of all your
business traffic? Maybe yes… maybe no… But the only way you can be certain is to
let the test continue to run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you declare a winner that is statistically significant but is &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt;
representative of your business traffic, you could be implementing a change that
actually hurts your business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going back to our version “A” gray button and version “B” orange button, let’s
say version “A” reaches statistical significance in one hour. If you peek at the
results early, you may see “A” as being the winner. However, if you let the test
continue to run, you’d end up with version “B” having a higher conversion rate
in the longer term with a larger sample size. In this scenario, the traffic in
the one hour was &lt;strong&gt;not indicative&lt;/strong&gt; of the larger conversion funnel trend where
version “B” was the true winner. This is why you shouldn&amp;rsquo;t peek at ongoing
tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This gets us back to the original question of how long to run a test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We recommend that A/B tests should be run through &lt;strong&gt;a minimum of two online
business cycles&lt;/strong&gt;. This helps to minimize the chance of anomalies and false
positives in the data. In theory, the data that comes from those two business
cycles should look pretty similar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How long is your online business cycle? An online business cycle usually ranges
from &lt;strong&gt;one to four weeks&lt;/strong&gt;, but will vary from business to business. It depends on
your consistent activities for &lt;strong&gt;driving traffic&lt;/strong&gt; to your business, but we’ll dive
into that another time. (If you’d like help figuring out your online business
cycle, just &lt;a href="mailto:3wojkp7a"&gt;shoot us an email&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you make the front page of a major site like &lt;a href="http://techcrunch.com"&gt;Tech
Crunch&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.reddit.com"&gt;reddit&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/"&gt;Hacker
News&lt;/a&gt; and get an &lt;em&gt;abnormal&lt;/em&gt; spike in traffic during
one cycle, be cautious when making any decisions. Ask yourself if that traffic
really represents your usual business. You should consider running the test even
longer to balance things out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this ladies and gentlemen is how a statistical answer to a business scenario
can be both correct &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; incorrect at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you have a basic understanding of A/B testing. So let’s spice things up a
little bit and get fancy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;6. Bonus Question: What do all of those marketing sales-y speak headlines &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; mean?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You think you have a handle on this A/B testing thing and then you come across a
headline like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&amp;ldquo;We’ll &lt;strong&gt;increase your conversions&lt;/strong&gt; by 30%!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Fancy Marketer&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That sounds great. Where do I sign up?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have probably seen similar sales-y headlines elsewhere. Maybe you are
thinking about that 3% increase in conversion rate earlier. The headline says
30%. Done!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;….&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wait a second… Take a closer look at that headline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It says “increase your conversions &lt;em&gt;by&lt;/em&gt;” a certain percentage.  Why is this one
word such a big deal?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time to break down the sales and marketing speak and understand what those
numbers &lt;em&gt;truly&lt;/em&gt; mean. Because the numbers &lt;em&gt;sound&lt;/em&gt; great, but they may not mean
what you think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Example:
Let’s again say you’re selling some software and your current conversion rate is
10%. We’ll go big with a 30% increase, improvement, or 
&lt;span data-tooltip aria-haspopup="true" class="has-tip" title="more fancy marketing speak"&gt;lift&lt;/span&gt;
on that original 10%. This actually means a &lt;em&gt;true&lt;/em&gt; 3% increase to your original
conversion rate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s &lt;strong&gt;how it works&lt;/strong&gt;. The 30% is applied to the 10% conversion rate, NOT the
total overall conversion rate. 30% of 10% is 3%. (Here’s how the math works
(.3) * (.1) = .03 or 3%.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In layman’s terms, a 30% increase means your old conversion rate of 10% is now
13%. Huh… that 30% seems a little misleading now, doesn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before you get too disappointed, as discussed before, a 3% increase to your
total conversion rate can be a huge &lt;strong&gt;boost to your revenue&lt;/strong&gt;. The best part is as
long as you have the traffic, your testing options to &lt;strong&gt;optimize your sales funnel&lt;/strong&gt;
are endless! The more leaks you patch and barriers you remove to conversions in
your sales funnel, the more you will increase your revenue. A/B testing can
help get you there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: you also need to remember that a 3% improvement in your conversion rate
doesn’t help much if you had to cut your prices in half to get it… But, that’s
for another article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frankly, we love using A/B testing to optimize conversion funnels. Why? Because
&lt;strong&gt;little changes&lt;/strong&gt; can have &lt;strong&gt;big results&lt;/strong&gt;, big changes can have even bigger results,
and they all compound together!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;What’s your next step? What are you going to test? We’d love to &lt;a href="mailto:3wojkp7a"&gt;hear about it&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have a question about what you just read, a question about something else
related to A/B testing, or just want to say hello? &lt;a href="mailto:3wojkp7a"&gt;Shoot us an email&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How to Update Fork from Original Github Repo</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://torspark.com/how-to-update-fork-from-original-github-repo/"/>
    <id>http://torspark.com/how-to-update-fork-from-original-github-repo/</id>
    <published>2014-11-02T19:27:00-06:00</published>
    <updated>2015-01-22T23:07:06-06:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Chris Olds</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;What do you do when you have a custom fork of a repository, and the original
version has some new update that you&amp;rsquo;d like to include in your fork without
losing your customizations? It&amp;rsquo;s a pretty simple process if you just follow the
steps below.
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;What do you do when you have a custom fork of a repository, and the original
version has some new update that you&amp;rsquo;d like to include in your fork without
losing your customizations? It&amp;rsquo;s a pretty simple process if you just follow the
steps below.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Add the original repo&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, you need to &lt;strong&gt;add the parent repo as a second remote&lt;/strong&gt; for your local
fork. You could name this remote after the original owner (ex: torspark), but I
like to name it &amp;ldquo;parent&amp;rdquo; to keep things simple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight shell"&gt;&lt;table style="border-spacing: 0"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="gutter gl" style="text-align: right"&gt;&lt;pre class="lineno"&gt;1&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="code"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;git remote add parent &amp;lt;url-to-parent-repo&amp;gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, I recently made a couple customizations to the
&lt;a href="http://rubygems.org/gems/middleman-spellcheck"&gt;middleman-spellcheck gem&lt;/a&gt;.
This started as a pull request to fix a bug, but then I added a little extra
functionality while I was digging into the code.  Anyway, after my pull request
was accepted, I wanted to update my fork to be based on the current version.
Here&amp;rsquo;s what I typed into my terminal:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight shell"&gt;&lt;table style="border-spacing: 0"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="gutter gl" style="text-align: right"&gt;&lt;pre class="lineno"&gt;1&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="code"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;git remote add parent git@github.com:minivan/middleman-spellcheck.git
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Verify that your remote was added by running:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight shell"&gt;&lt;table style="border-spacing: 0"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="gutter gl" style="text-align: right"&gt;&lt;pre class="lineno"&gt;1&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="code"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;git remote
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Fetch the original repo&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, you can &lt;strong&gt;fetch all the changes&lt;/strong&gt; from the original repo by typing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight shell"&gt;&lt;table style="border-spacing: 0"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="gutter gl" style="text-align: right"&gt;&lt;pre class="lineno"&gt;1&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="code"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;git fetch parent
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will give you a new branch called parent/master. If you&amp;rsquo;re looking for a
specific branch on the parent repository, the following command with list all
branches available, including both those from your fork and the parent repo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight shell"&gt;&lt;table style="border-spacing: 0"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="gutter gl" style="text-align: right"&gt;&lt;pre class="lineno"&gt;1&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="code"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;git branch -a
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Merge or Rebase&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, you just have to either merge or &lt;strong&gt;rebase your branch&lt;/strong&gt; with the parent
repo. If you prefer to merge, checkout your branch, and merge the branch you
want from the parent repo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight shell"&gt;&lt;table style="border-spacing: 0"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="gutter gl" style="text-align: right"&gt;&lt;pre class="lineno"&gt;1
2&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="code"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;git checkout master
git merge parent/master
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, if you&amp;rsquo;re a fan of rebasing code, you can run this instead:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight shell"&gt;&lt;table style="border-spacing: 0"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="gutter gl" style="text-align: right"&gt;&lt;pre class="lineno"&gt;1&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="code"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;git rebase parent/master
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was the only one using my fork at the time, so I chose to rebase in order to
have a cleaner version history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s all there is to it. The features I added have since been pulled into the
original repo, so you can see that
&lt;a href="https://github.com/torspark/middleman-spellcheck"&gt;my fork&lt;/a&gt;
matches the
&lt;a href="https://github.com/minivan/middleman-spellcheck"&gt;original repo&lt;/a&gt; (as of version
0.7.5). This process will make it easy for me to continue adding new feature
branches to my fork while staying current with the original repository as more
pull requests are accepted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What repositories have you contributed to lately? I&amp;rsquo;d love to
&lt;a href="mailto:3wojkp7a"&gt;hear about it&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How to Calculate Article Reading Time with a Custom Middleman Extension</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://torspark.com/how-to-calculate-article-reading-time-with-a-custom-middleman-extension/"/>
    <id>http://torspark.com/how-to-calculate-article-reading-time-with-a-custom-middleman-extension/</id>
    <published>2014-10-20T21:58:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2015-01-22T23:09:10-06:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Chris Olds</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is a quick how-to guide on implementing an estimated reading time feature
for your &lt;a href="http://middlemanapp.com"&gt;Middleman&lt;/a&gt; blog with a custom Middleman
extension.
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is a quick how-to guide on implementing an estimated reading time feature
for your &lt;a href="http://middlemanapp.com"&gt;Middleman&lt;/a&gt; blog with a custom Middleman
extension.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Write the custom extension&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can just drop the code below into the main directory for your Middleman
project. Mine is under &lt;code&gt;torspark.com/reading_time.rb&lt;/code&gt;. Note that this is above
the &lt;code&gt;/source&lt;/code&gt; directory where most of your work will go in a Middleman project.
You could also put it in a top level &lt;code&gt;/extensions&lt;/code&gt; directory alongside the
&lt;code&gt;/source&lt;/code&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;code&gt;/build&lt;/code&gt; directories if you plan to write a lot of custom
extensions. I don&amp;rsquo;t have a need for this yet, so I just left it as an individual
file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight ruby"&gt;&lt;table style="border-spacing: 0"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="gutter gl" style="text-align: right"&gt;&lt;pre class="lineno"&gt;1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10
11
12
13
14
15
16
17
18
19
20
21&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="code"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Outputs the reading time&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# ex: Read this in "about 3 minutes"&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nc"&gt;ReadingTime&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="no"&gt;Middleman&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="no"&gt;Extension&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;initialize&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;app&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;options_hash&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;{},&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;block&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;super&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="k"&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class="n"&gt;helpers&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;reading_time&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;input&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="n"&gt;words_per_minute&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;180&lt;/span&gt;

      &lt;span class="n"&gt;words&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;input&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;split&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;size&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="n"&gt;minutes&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;words&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="sr"&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;/&lt;span class="sr"&gt;words_per_minute).floor
      minutes_label = minutes === 1 ? ' minute' : ' minutes'
      minutes &amp;gt; 0 ? "about &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;#{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;minutes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="sr"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;#{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;minutes_label&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="sr"&gt;" : 'less than 1 minute'
    end
  end
end

::Middleman::Extensions.register(:reading_time, ReadingTime)
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can easily customize line #11 to match the average reading speed for your
readers. &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Words_per_minute"&gt;180 words per minute&lt;/a&gt;
is a conservative estimate for proofreading on a monitor. The average adult can
read between 250 to 300 words per minute. Most of my articles are at least a
little technical, so I decided to stick with 180 wpm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lines #13&amp;ndash;16 calculate the total number of words in the article, and then
pluralize the label if necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last line registers the extension so you can activate it in the &lt;code&gt;config.rb&lt;/code&gt;
file, like the code below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Activate &amp;amp; use your extension&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight ruby"&gt;&lt;table style="border-spacing: 0"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="gutter gl" style="text-align: right"&gt;&lt;pre class="lineno"&gt;1
2&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="code"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;require&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;'reading_time'&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;activate&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;reading_time&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, we just need to use the helper in our layout. The estimated reading times
you can see on
&lt;a title="Build Better Software, Faster" href="http://torspark.com"&gt;Torspark&amp;rsquo;s home page&lt;/a&gt;
and in the upper right of this page (assuming I haven&amp;rsquo;t redesigned things&amp;hellip;)
are generated with the code below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight ruby"&gt;&lt;table style="border-spacing: 0"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="gutter gl" style="text-align: right"&gt;&lt;pre class="lineno"&gt;1
2
3
4
5
6
7&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="code"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# links on source/index.html.haml:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;link_to&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;"Read this article in &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;#{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;reading_time&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;article&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;body&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;article&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Estimated reading time in source/layouts/article.haml:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;p&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="no"&gt;Read&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;this&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;article&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;reading_time&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;current_article&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;body&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Alternative&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For something this simple, you could just drop lines #10&amp;ndash;17 from the first code
block above into the helper section of your Middleman &lt;code&gt;config.rb&lt;/code&gt; file. I went
ahead and built out the full extension, because I&amp;rsquo;m planning to flesh it out a
little more. The separate file also makes things a little cleaner to manage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Feedback? Questions?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s all there is to writing and using your own custom extension for
Middleman. I hope it helps you customize your site. I&amp;rsquo;d love to hear about the
custom extensions you use. &lt;a href="mailto:3wojkp7a"&gt;Drop me a line&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Should I make a gem for you?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I&amp;rsquo;d consider building this out a little more and making a gem if you&amp;rsquo;re
interested. &lt;a href="mailto:3wojkp7a"&gt;Let me know&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Benefits of Weekly Billing for Clients</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://torspark.com/benefits-of-weekly-billing-for-clients/"/>
    <id>http://torspark.com/benefits-of-weekly-billing-for-clients/</id>
    <published>2014-10-17T18:02:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2014-10-28T01:32:32-05:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Chris Olds</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Do you really want to pay 50% up front for your project, before you&amp;rsquo;ve even had
a chance to build a rapport with your developer? Is it a pain to get upper
management to approve that big down payment? Or are you having trouble tracking
&amp;amp; budgeting for various hourly invoices? You&amp;rsquo;re a good client, of course, but do
you want your consultant wasting his time trying to collect fees from other less
reputable clients?
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Do you really want to pay 50% up front for your project, before you&amp;rsquo;ve even had
a chance to build a rapport with your developer? Is it a pain to get upper
management to approve that big down payment? Or are you having trouble tracking
&amp;amp; budgeting for various hourly invoices? You&amp;rsquo;re a good client, of course, but do
you want your consultant wasting his time trying to collect fees from other less
reputable clients?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe the developer you hired turned out to be a hack. Or your dev just doesn&amp;rsquo;t
seem to have enough time for you. Or they don&amp;rsquo;t communicate with you as much as
you&amp;rsquo;d like. Whatever the reason, now you&amp;rsquo;re wondering how you can salvage some
of that hefty down payment or if you just have to try to make the most of the
situation. It may seem a little scary at first, but up front weekly billing can
help you avoid these situations. See the benefits below, or read about
&lt;a title="Charging weekly will make you happier" href="/advantages-of-weekly-billing-for-developers/"&gt;weekly billing from a developer&amp;rsquo;s perspective&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Why you should want to be charged weekly as a client&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Easy on your budget&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Weekly payments are easy to budget.&lt;/strong&gt; You know exactly how much you&amp;rsquo;ll need to
pay each week. A lot of managers can even just use their discretionary fund to
pay for development, rather than having to get a 50% down payment approved by
upper management. If you&amp;rsquo;re a small business, you can easily make payments with
your credit card, and not worry about a large upfront payment putting your
business at risk by becoming cash poor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Limit your risk&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By paying weekly, you can &lt;strong&gt;limit the risk&lt;/strong&gt; of getting stuck with a bad
developer. If you aren&amp;rsquo;t satisfied with the past week&amp;rsquo;s worth of work, you are
free to stop paying and find a new developer. No need to feel like you&amp;rsquo;re
committed to a slow developer. No need to worry about how to get the most out of
your down payment or even trying to recoup some of it in court. At worst, you&amp;rsquo;re
out just a week&amp;rsquo;s worth of money, and that&amp;rsquo;s it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Know your developer is focused on your project&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By paying your developer for a week&amp;rsquo;s worth of work in advance, you can be
secure in the knowledge that &lt;strong&gt;your developer is focused on your project&lt;/strong&gt;. You
don&amp;rsquo;t really want them working on your project for a couple hours here and there
among the other projects on their plate. That just slows the development down
and decreases the quality, because of all the context switching they&amp;rsquo;re going
through, bouncing from project to project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;ll also get the added benefit of having a &lt;strong&gt;faster and more motivated
developer&lt;/strong&gt;. If you&amp;rsquo;re paying hourly invoices, the slower your dev works, the
more money they&amp;rsquo;ll receive. Is that right? Your developer should be an expert
professional. If they know you trust them to provide value, they&amp;rsquo;ll be
encouraged to work as efficiently as possible, because procrastinating won&amp;rsquo;t
make them any more money. There&amp;rsquo;s also the push to deliver value &lt;em&gt;every single
week&lt;/em&gt;, because they know you could choose to just end the engagement at any
time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Why waste your time arguing over what&amp;rsquo;s in scope&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paying weekly means you don&amp;rsquo;t have to constantly check the original scope
document to see if you can request this or that little change. Let&amp;rsquo;s face it,
that scope document is usually out of date &lt;em&gt;within a week&lt;/em&gt; of signing it. You
won&amp;rsquo;t have to waste time on addendums to the original contract, because you can
just as for the change, knowing that you&amp;rsquo;ve already paid for this week&amp;rsquo;s work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, weekly billing doesn&amp;rsquo;t sound so scary does it? If you give it a chance, I
bet you&amp;rsquo;ll even prefer it. If your developer isn&amp;rsquo;t charging weekly, maybe you
should ask them why not? You could send them a link to the
&lt;a title="The best way to charge as a consultant" href="/advantages-of-weekly-billing-for-developers/"&gt;advantages of weekly billing for consultants&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Advantages of Weekly Billing for Developers</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://torspark.com/advantages-of-weekly-billing-for-developers/"/>
    <id>http://torspark.com/advantages-of-weekly-billing-for-developers/</id>
    <published>2014-10-17T17:07:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2014-10-28T01:44:17-05:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Chris Olds</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Why does weekly billing make more sense for both clients and consultants? Do
you really want to waste valuable client time collecting payments? Are you
tired of arguing over hourly line items?
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Why does weekly billing make more sense for both clients and consultants? Do
you really want to waste valuable client time collecting payments? Are you
tired of arguing over hourly line items?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weekly billing is good for you &amp;amp; your business. It might sound scary at first,
but you and your clients will both be happier in the long run. You might want to
check out this article
&lt;a title="Why would I want to pay up front weekly?" href="/benefits-of-weekly-billing-for-clients/"&gt;from a client&amp;rsquo;s perspective&lt;/a&gt;, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Why you should bill weekly as a developer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you ever started a project with the best intentions, but things just went
south? Maybe you just can&amp;rsquo;t seem to communicate with your client, or they&amp;rsquo;re
constantly asking for scope changes, or falling behind on payments. If you agreed
on the usual terms (50% up front and 50% upon completion), or some variation, then
you&amp;rsquo;re both out of luck. Maybe you&amp;rsquo;re realizing that you&amp;rsquo;ll have to find a way to
endure x number of weeks until you can finish the project and receive the other 50%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;50/50 billing is broken.&lt;/strong&gt; Both parties are exposed to risk than they need to be.
The client takes on a lot of risk up front, especially if they&amp;rsquo;ve never worked
with this dev before. On the other end, the developer ends up with all the risk
for the back half of the project. What if the client keeps asking for more and
more changes, holding that paycheck over your head? Or worst case, what if they
keep delaying payment? Is it worth your time to track them down and maybe even
sue them? No.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Weekly billing is the answer.&lt;/strong&gt; It limits risk for everyone involved. At
&lt;a title="Custom Software Dev Shop with weekly pricing" href="/"&gt;Torspark&lt;/a&gt;,
I charge up front for a week&amp;rsquo;s worth of work. Below are the reasons why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s your motivation?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re invoicing based on an hourly rate, are you really motivated to be
productive? Think about the incentives. The slower you work, the more money you
get&amp;hellip; Does that make any sense?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting paid for a week at a time will motivate you to &lt;em&gt;be as productive as
possible&lt;/em&gt;. The faster you work, the higher your effective &amp;ldquo;hourly&amp;rdquo; rate becomes.
This makes a lot more sense. Your clients will be happy with how quickly you
knock out tasks, and your income won&amp;rsquo;t be capped by a strict $/hour rate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Tracking time is a waste of time&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How much time do you spend each week tracking your time? How accurate are you?
Down to the minute? Round up 15 minutes? Approximately half an hour? It all
turns into a &lt;em&gt;guesstimate&lt;/em&gt; anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How much time do you think you lose switching back and forth from productive
work to time tracking? I bet it&amp;rsquo;s more than you think. You could probably
claim it takes you less than a minute, but are you considering the context shift
your brain has to go through in the process? You&amp;rsquo;ve heard
&lt;a href="http://www.smh.com.au/small-business/trends/why-multitasking-is-bad-20131202-2yl3s.html"&gt;multitasking&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/work-in-progress/2013/01/15/how-multitasking-hurts-your-brain-and-your-effectiveness-at-work/"&gt;is&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/nova/body/is-multitasking-bad.html"&gt;bad&lt;/a&gt;.
Time tracking is just another form of multitasking. If you&amp;rsquo;re a coder, I&amp;rsquo;m sure
you&amp;rsquo;ve experienced the loss of productivity after having your mental model of
the problem disappear after an interruption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Side note:
&lt;a href="http://heeris.id.au/2013/this-is-why-you-shouldnt-interrupt-a-programmer/"&gt;never interrupt a programmer&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are you supposed to bill for the time spent documenting your time on each task?
That&amp;rsquo;s a gray area. It isn&amp;rsquo;t real work, but it&amp;rsquo;s work you wouldn&amp;rsquo;t have to do
if you weren&amp;rsquo;t working on a client project&amp;hellip; You don&amp;rsquo;t have to worry about it
either way if you just stop charging hourly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t get me wrong, I think it&amp;rsquo;s smart to have a good idea of how you&amp;rsquo;re
spending you time. But, the level of detail that hourly invoices require?
Unnecessary. When you do want to get an idea of where you&amp;rsquo;re spending your
time, I recommend using &lt;a href="https://www.toggl.com/"&gt;Toggl&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Scope creep will happen, and that&amp;rsquo;s ok&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can be very hard to maintain your margin when selling a project at a fixed
price. There are always changes to be made, that you and your client can&amp;rsquo;t
possibly know about until after the project is under way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Could we just change that one &amp;ldquo;little&amp;rdquo; thing real quick?
&lt;cite&gt; Your Friendly Client &lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a fixed bid, you have to make a comprehensive document detailing exactly
what is and is not in scope. Then you&amp;rsquo;ll either have to act like a lawyer,
referring to it every time the client wants to make a change, or eat the cost of
making &amp;ldquo;one more little tweak&amp;rdquo; over &amp;amp; over. This doesn&amp;rsquo;t hurt too much here or
there, but it adds up fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With hourly billing, there&amp;rsquo;s often a disconnect between what might be perceived
as a simple change, and what could take you a few hours more than the client
expected. This leads to arguments over what exactly were you doing for those
three and a half hours on task #122. Of course, they don&amp;rsquo;t usually notice the
big feature that you were able to deliver in half the time expected thanks to
your expertise. Any given task might take a little longer than expected, but
there are just as many that you&amp;rsquo;ll finish faster than expected, They usually
even out over the course of a week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;You are not a bank&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You shouldn&amp;rsquo;t have to spend time tracking down overdue invoices when you could
be delivering value to your clients. For any decent-sized project, &lt;strong&gt;weekly
billing limits your exposure&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;amp; your client&amp;rsquo;s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re billing hourly, all of the exposure risk is on you, the consultant.
You do a bunch of work for x number of hours, then send off an invoice, hoping
to get paid within the terms of your agreement, which could be anywhere from net
15 days to 90+. That&amp;rsquo;s like an interest free loan just sitting out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re charging a fixed price for a project, you usually collect payments
upon achieving milestones. The simplest being 50% down, with 50% upon
completion. Sometimes it could be paid it quarters or thirds, or even
30/30/30/10. All of these options help spread the risk a little, but &lt;em&gt;you&amp;rsquo;re
still stuck trying to collect payments&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Weekly billing makes it so you never have to act like a collection agency.&lt;/strong&gt;
You get paid for a week&amp;rsquo;s worth of work up front. You don&amp;rsquo;t have the liability
of receiving a full 50% up front. Your client only has the limited risk of one
week&amp;rsquo;s worth of payments. If they aren&amp;rsquo;t happy, they&amp;rsquo;re free to stop the project
at anytime, without worrying about the big down payment they may have already
sunk into this project. This should help motivate you to consistently do good
work and deliver value too&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might take a little convincing, but you and your clients will both be happier
in the long run if you switch over to billing weekly for your services. If your
clients need a little convincing, encourage them to check out the
&lt;a title="Do you trust your developer?" href="/benefits-of-weekly-billing-for-clients/"&gt;benefits of weekly billing for clients&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Static Site Generators: Jekyll vs Octopress vs Middleman</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://torspark.com/static-site-generators-jekyll-vs-octopress-vs-middleman/"/>
    <id>http://torspark.com/static-site-generators-jekyll-vs-octopress-vs-middleman/</id>
    <published>2014-10-14T22:15:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2014-10-28T01:53:56-05:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Chris Olds</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;So, I finally rebuilt this site last week.
With so many choices, choosing a framework can be tough.
After a lot of research, I narrowed it down to &lt;a href="http://jekyllrb.com"&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="http://octopress.org"&gt;Octopress&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href="http://middlemanapp.com"&gt;Middleman&lt;/a&gt;.
Now, I just had to choose&amp;hellip;
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So, I finally rebuilt this site last week.
With so many choices, choosing a framework can be tough.
After a lot of research, I narrowed it down to &lt;a href="http://jekyllrb.com"&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="http://octopress.org"&gt;Octopress&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href="http://middlemanapp.com"&gt;Middleman&lt;/a&gt;.
Now, I just had to choose&amp;hellip;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Why use a static site generator?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years, &lt;a title="Software Consultancy" href="http://torspark.com,"&gt;torspark.com&lt;/a&gt; has
gone through several variations and false starts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was originally a &lt;a href="http://wordpress.com"&gt;Wordpress&lt;/a&gt; several years ago, but
that never felt quite right.
I prefer working in Ruby, so it was never fun digging back into the PHP world
to customize a plugin or theme.
Plus, Wordpress is just too bloated for my needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I considered building a full-fledged Rails or Sinatra application, but that
seemed like overkill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Static sites are great for ditching databases &amp;amp; conserving server resources.
They lets you serve content to more people faster &amp;amp; for less money.
Static site generators have come a long way.
In fact, they&amp;rsquo;re a pleasure to work with now.
If I can manage to avoid using a database on a project, I will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Jekyll&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve used Jekyll to build a few client sites before, so I was pretty familiar
with it.
Github pages integration is nice, but limited by not being able to use
custom plugins.
Of course, you can still build your site locally and then push it up, but you
could do that with Octopress or Middleman too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I work faster with HAML and SASS, and I was able to hack on Jekyll enough to
let me do so (for the most part), but it never felt very clean.
I started building out this site in Jekyll for awhile, but never finished it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll is the most popular static site generator, but it just wasn&amp;rsquo;t for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Octopress&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Octopress is built on top of Jekyll.
It&amp;rsquo;s designed to be more opinionated and blog-friendly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Octopress gets the job done, but it&amp;rsquo;s docs and development seem to be lacking.
Essentially a highly customized version of Jekyll, it will always be slower
to get new Jekyll features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a partially built Octopress version of this site rotting away somewhere
on my hard drive too&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Middleman&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, after two false starts, I&amp;rsquo;ve found the perfect static site builder for me.
Middleman is billed as a &amp;ldquo;static site generator using all the shortcuts and tools
in modern web development.&amp;rdquo;
That&amp;rsquo;s true&amp;mdash;Middleman comes with HAML, SASS, &amp;amp; Coffeescript built in.
Meaning I don&amp;rsquo;t have to waste time hacking on it to speed up my workflow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has a blog plugin to match everything Octopress can do.
If you&amp;rsquo;re familiar with Rails, it&amp;rsquo;s easy to add helpers and extra functionality
in a similar fashion.
The built-in Live Reload feature is awesome.
I usually set up some form of live-reloading to speed up frontend development
on my projects, and having it built-in was just icing on the cake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll and Octopress are both good choices, but I found that Middleman lets
me work faster and happier.
Jekyll is probably the easiest to get started with, but if you know ruby,
Middleman gives you a lot more power &amp;amp; freedom.
Any static sites I build in the foreseeable future will be built with Middleman.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
