<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Torspark</title>
  <subtitle>Custom Software Development &amp; Consultancy</subtitle>
  <id>http://torspark.com/</id>
  <link href="http://torspark.com/"/>
  <link href="http://torspark.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2014-10-14T22:15:00-05:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Chris Olds</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Static Site Generators: Jekyll vs Octopress vs Middleman</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://torspark.com/static-site-generators-jekyll-vs-octopress-vs-middleman/"/>
    <id>http://torspark.com/static-site-generators-jekyll-vs-octopress-vs-middleman/</id>
    <published>2014-10-14T22:15:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2014-10-15T02:02:22-05:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Chris Olds</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;So, I finally rebuilt this site last week.
With so many choices, choosing a framework can be tough.
After a lot of research, I narrowed it down to &lt;a href="http://jekyllrb.com"&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="http://octopress.org"&gt;Octopress&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href="http://middlemanapp.com"&gt;Middleman&lt;/a&gt;.
Now, I just had to choose&amp;hellip;
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So, I finally rebuilt this site last week.
With so many choices, choosing a framework can be tough.
After a lot of research, I narrowed it down to &lt;a href="http://jekyllrb.com"&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="http://octopress.org"&gt;Octopress&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href="http://middlemanapp.com"&gt;Middleman&lt;/a&gt;.
Now, I just had to choose&amp;hellip;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Why use a static site generator?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years, &lt;a title="Software Consultancy" href="http://torspark.com,"&gt;torspark.com&lt;/a&gt; has
gone through several variations and false starts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was originally a &lt;a href="http://wordpress.com"&gt;Wordpress&lt;/a&gt; several years ago, but
that never felt quite right.
I prefer working in Ruby, so it was never fun digging back into the PHP world
to customize a plugin or theme.
Plus, Wordpress is just too bloated for my needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I considered building a full-fledged Rails or Sinatra application, but that
seemed like overkill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Static sites are great for ditching databases &amp;amp; conserving server resources.
They lets you serve content to more people faster &amp;amp; for less money.
Static site generators have come a long way.
In fact, they&amp;rsquo;re a pleasure to work with now.
If I can manage to avoid using a database on a project, I will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Jekyll&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve used Jekyll to build a few client sites before, so I was pretty familiar
with it.
Github pages integration is nice, but limited by not being able to use
custom plugins.
Of course, you can still build your site locally and then push it up, but you
could do that with Octopress or Middleman too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I work faster with HAML and SASS, and I was able to hack on Jekyll enough to
let me do so (for the most part), but it never felt very clean.
I started building out this site in Jekyll for awhile, but never finished it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll is the most popular static site generator, but it just wasn&amp;rsquo;t for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Octopress&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Octopress is built on top of Jekyll.
It&amp;rsquo;s designed to be more opinionated and blog-friendly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Octopress gets the job done, but it&amp;rsquo;s docs and development seem to be lacking.
Essentially a highly customized version of Jekyll, it will always be slower
to get new Jekyll features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a partially built Octopress version of this site rotting away somewhere
on my hard drive too&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Middleman&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, after two false starts, I&amp;rsquo;ve found the perfect static site builder for me.
Middlman is billed as a &amp;ldquo;static site generator using all the shortcuts and tools
in modern web development.&amp;rdquo;
That&amp;rsquo;s true&amp;mdash;Middleman comes with HAML, SASS, &amp;amp; Coffeescript built in.
Meaning I don&amp;rsquo;t have to waste time hacking on it to speed up my workflow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has a blog plugin to match everything Octopress can do.
If you&amp;rsquo;re familiar with Rails, it&amp;rsquo;s easy to add helpers and extra functionality
in a similar fashion.
The built-in Live Reload feature is awesome.
I usually set up some form of live-reloading to speed up frontend development
on my projects, and having it built-in was just icing on the cake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll and Octopress are both good choices, but I found that Middleman lets
me work faster and happier.
Any static sites I build in the foreseeable future will be built with Middleman.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
