<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Torspark</title>
  <subtitle>Custom Software Development &amp; Consultancy</subtitle>
  <id>http://torspark.com</id>
  <link href="http://torspark.com"/>
  <link href="http://torspark.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2015-02-25T08:24:00-06:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Chris Olds</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Bandit Testing: When Should You Use Multi-Armed Bandit Testing</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://torspark.com/bandit-testing-when-should-you-use-multi-armed-bandit-testing/"/>
    <id>http://torspark.com/bandit-testing-when-should-you-use-multi-armed-bandit-testing/</id>
    <published>2015-02-25T08:24:00-06:00</published>
    <updated>2015-02-25T13:17:33-06:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Tania Lyerly</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Split testing. When you hear the term split testing, most people assume it is
referring to A/B testing. And typically you would be correct. However,
technically A/B testing is a type of split testing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bandit testing is another type of split testing...&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Split testing. When you hear the term split testing, most people assume it is
referring to A/B testing. And typically you would be correct. However,
technically A/B testing is a type of split testing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bandit testing is another type of split testing. If you’ve been doing research
into conversion rate optimization, split testing, or A/B testing, then you have
probably come across bandit testing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More technically known as multi-armed bandit testing, it is an alternative
approach to split testing compared to A/B split testing. Just because bandit
testing offers a different approach does not mean you should take it. This
article will answer the following questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is multi-armed bandit testing?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How is multi-armed bandit testing different from A/B testing?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the benefits of multi-armed bandit testing?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the disadvantages to multi-armed bandit testing?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s jump right into things, shall we!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;1. What is multi-armed bandit testing?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="row of slot machines" src="/img/empty-slot-machines.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not to be confused with our raccoon friend, multi-armed bandit testing comes
from a gambling scenario. A gambler is in front of a row of slot machines (aka
one armed bandits, hence the name). The gambler knows that each machine has its
own algorithm of rewards. Some machines payout better than others. The trick is
to figure out which machines offer the better rate of return and maximize it.
The gambler will have &lt;strong&gt;two phases: explorative and exploitative&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the explorative phase the gambler will put coins into all of the
machines equally to test which gives the higher returns (aka conversions). Then
during the exploitative phase, the gambler starts to put more coins (traffic)
in the machines that have the higher rewards. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;How bandit testing works with your website&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of three slot machines, we have three versions of your website (A, B,
and C). &lt;strong&gt;Our explorative and exploitative phases run indefinitely&lt;/strong&gt; (or until
we end the test). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, we can set the explorative level at 10% and the exploitative level
at 90%. (This ratio can be changed as desired). Let’s use 10,000 visitors for
an easy number. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means 10% of traffic (1,000 visitors) will “explore” the variations.
Traffic is evenly distributed across all three options. The other 90% of
traffic (9,000 visitors) will be proportionally directed to the versions with
the higher conversion rates. The 90% exploits the results from the 10%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;2. How is multi-armed bandit testing different from A/B testing?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you remember from the &lt;a href="/ab-testing-crash-course-5-questions-and-answers-you-need-to-know/"&gt;A/B testing crash course
article&lt;/a&gt;,
traffic during an A/B test is split evenly between the different variations. In
our A/B/C example above, our split test would direct 33% of traffic to each
version. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With A/B testing, versions that aren’t performing as well continue to receive
the same amount of traffic as the versions with a higher conversion rate. In a
bandit test, the versions with the higher conversion rates receive a higher
proportion of traffic. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;3. What are the benefits of multi-armed bandit testing?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;When time is not on your side: sales or other seasonality.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is hands down &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; benefit to running a multi-armed bandit test over an
A/B test. An A/B test could run 2 weeks or even 6+ weeks long to properly
determine a winner. (A combination of statistical significance and running the
test over multiple business cycles.) Then you implement the winner on your site
for the foreseeable future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A/B tests don’t work well if you are having a sale that lasts only 3 weeks
(kind of irrelevant actually). Your goal is optimizing conversions during the
sale. A multi-armed bandit test does this. You don’t care about the foreseeable
future because there isn’t a future after the limited window of the sale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;If you are very risk averse when it comes to testing, this could be the test for you.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Honestly, I debated whether to list this as a benefit or not. Here’s why: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are very risk averse, you probably aren’t doing any kind of serious
testing. Even the best hypothesis must get tested eventually to prove its
worth. It could fail, or it could sky-rocket your conversions. You just don’t
know until you test it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, with bandit testing you get to be greedy. Traffic gets pushed to the
higher performing variations. This means you are maximizing your conversions.
&lt;em&gt;But&lt;/em&gt; this may not bode well for confidently determining the winning version.
(I’ll explain this more in the disadvantages section below.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If maximizing conversions is the name of the game, then…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Why doesn’t everyone use bandit testing instead of A/B testing?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a great question. Bandit testing has its select benefits, but it has
many disadvantages. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;4. What are the disadvantages to multi-armed bandit testing?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Say it with me, &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Set it and forget!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are a lazy tester, then this is a benefit. For the rest of us, it’s a
severe disadvantage. As a serious tester, you want to determine a winner as
efficiently (and quickly) as possible. Then once you have your winner you can
run your next test. Think of it like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You test version B against your current version (A). Version B wins. Then you
test version C against B (the new original). Version B wins again. Next, you
test version D. Version D beats version B. Version D becomes the new standard. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an example of the ongoing testing you should be conducting. The more
versions you test at once, the longer the test will take to determine a winner.
Which is why it is better to limit the number of versions at one time, unless
you have a &lt;em&gt;ton&lt;/em&gt; of traffic. Also, you may not have thought B would win, or
other insights came out of the test. As a result of these insights, version C
is born.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By continuously testing, you can continuously make improvements to your website
and conversion funnel.This is the only way to continue to maximize conversions,
revenue, and profit in the long term. If you “set it and forget” you aren’t
continuously improving. Instead, you are stuck in a rut and money is left on
the table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bandit tests are better used as a strategy in a specific setting rather than as
a test in the traditional A/B testing sense. Here’s why: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A bandit test can run indefinitely. It will run until the code is deleted, or
until the end of the world as we know it. Whichever happens first. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is great if you want to run a test forever. It is not so great if you want
to choose and implement a winning version. Which brings me to my next several
points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;The short term conversion benefit can hurt your conversion rate in the long term.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Used in the right situation, a bandit test can be a great tool in your testing
tool belt. However, the use of bandit testing should generally be the exception
rather than the rule. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the short term, your conversions are maximized. Most traffic is pushed to
the best performing version. In the long term, some percentage of traffic is
always directed towards all versions. This includes the versions not performing
as well. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The exploration phase never stops during a bandit test.&lt;/strong&gt; It&amp;rsquo;s part of the
code. The percentage of traffic that makes up the explorative segment can be
changed, but it never fully disappears.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In laymen’s terms, the losers are always getting some traffic, unlike with an
A/B test where the winning version is eventually implemented. As a result
&lt;strong&gt;with bandit testing you lose out on a certain amount of conversions in the
long term&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe you are thinking at this point, “why can’t I have the best of both A/B
testing and bandit testing?” In theory, you run the bandit test to maximize
conversions until a winner is determined. Then delete the bandit testing code
and implement the winner. &lt;em&gt;In theory&lt;/em&gt; this works, in practicality there are
several problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Multi-armed bandit testing can take 5+ times longer to determine a winner than A/B testing.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visual Website Optimizer (VWO) ran a scenario with 3 website versions. They had
the following conversion rates: A=10%, B=15%, and C=20%. Additionally they ran
the simulation through 4 testing algorithms as denoted below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Simple randomization of A/B testing: &lt;em&gt;RAND&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multi-armed bandit (10% exploration, 90% exploitation): &lt;em&gt;MAB-10&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multi-armed bandit (50% exploration, 50% exploitation): &lt;em&gt;MAB-50&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multi-armed bandit (77% exploration, 23% exploitation): &lt;em&gt;MAB-77&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They waited for statistical significance to be found at least 10 times. These
were the results:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="iteration # when statistical significance was achieved" src="/img/vwo-bandit-vs-ab-1.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, the highest conversion rate happened with the bandit test that
had the highest exploitation. However, it took &lt;strong&gt;almost 6 times as much traffic
to declare significance&lt;/strong&gt;. This goes back to what I said above about short term
gains. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the test, you optimize your conversions. But, none of the tests beat out
the 20% conversion rate of C. If you want to maximize your conversion rate long
term, you want to declare a winner as efficiently as possible. Then implement
it. In this case, version C.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;VWO ran a different simulation to test statistical significance when the
conversion rates were minimally different (10% vs 11%). The simulations were
run 25 times with 10,000 iterations.Their findings did not bode well for bandit
tests. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="number of times no statistical significance was seen" src="/img/vwo-bandit-vs-ab-2.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;bandit testing simulations needed more traffic to declare statistical
significance.  &lt;em&gt;And&lt;/em&gt; they were more likely not to reach statistical
significance at all&lt;/strong&gt;. Determining if a test won’t achieve statistical
significance &amp;ndash;or if there isn’t a clear conversion rate winner&amp;ndash; is crucial.
The faster that is determined, the sooner you can run a new test. Which is why
A/B testing is often the better testing choice over a multi-armed bandit test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bandit testing may inaccurately allocate traffic to variations that are actually less effective based on business cycles.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All businesses have cycles. Conversion rates often change based on daily,
weekly, and even monthly business cycles. Let’s say most of your business
during a week happens Wednesday-Friday. You start a bandit test on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on Monday and Tuesday’s conversion rates more traffic is allocated
towards version A instead of B or C. However, Monday and Tuesday are not your
&lt;em&gt;”real”&lt;/em&gt; business days. Meaning, the results from Monday and Tuesday indicating
that A is the best converter, could be a false positive of sorts. Eventually
&lt;strong&gt;the bandit test will correct itself, but the damage to lost conversions will
have been done&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bandit tests assume that time variables don’t exist. This is generally not the
case in the business world. If your business has any kind of cyclical nature to
it (most businesses do), it is better to set up an A/B test that runs over the
entire cycle. You will receive a better, more holistic view of the different
conversion rates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Users can get confused with different versions and variations.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During an A/B test, users are sorted to see the different versions or
variations via a cookie. They will always see the same version until a new (or
winning) version is implemented. This is not the case with bandit testing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traffic and users are directed to the version with the highest conversion rate.
A user could see version A during an exploration phase. Then during the
exploitation phase that same user could see version B. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there is a shift in the conversion rate, or a change in the
exploration/exploitation levels, the user could be directed back to version A.
Or even to version C, if there is one. Basically, this makes for a confusing
user experience. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="two raccoons" src="/img/two-raccoons.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Multi-armed bandit tests are a great strategy to use when you want to
maximize conversions in a short time frame.&lt;/strong&gt; Main example of this is for
sales. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally, bandit tests should not be used as an ongoing strategy for your
website. &lt;strong&gt;A/B tests are the best testing strategy to efficiently make site
choices.&lt;/strong&gt; (I.e. What version of copy goes on your sign-up button. Or what
color should the button be- green or red.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Regardless of whether you are running a multi-armed bandit test or an A/B
test, use good testing practices.&lt;/strong&gt; This means knowing the conditions for
stopping the test: length of time and statistical significance level. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some testing software automatically sets a test length for 7 days and 95%
statistical significance. This does not mean those are the right conditions for
your test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that you’re armed with the knowledge of when to use multi-armed bandit
tests, feel free to implement it into your site. Just make sure you’re using it
for the right reasons. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’d like some help setting up a custom bandit solution, check out our
&lt;a href="/consulting/"&gt;consulting options&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P.S.  For those interested in the more technical aspects of split testing &amp;mdash;
multi-armed bandit testing is a type of greedy algorithm. It can also be referred
to as an epsilon-greedy strategy. A/B split testing is considered an
epsilon-first strategy&amp;hellip; Just in case you were curious. :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P.P.S. There will be another article going into greater depth on all of these
technicalities at some point. &lt;a href="/newsletter/"&gt;Join our mailing list&lt;/a&gt; to be the
first to know about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://eegaas.deviantart.com/art/Curious-raccoon-baby-272134880"&gt;Feature image credit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Why Carousels Destroy your Conversion Rate</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://torspark.com/why-carousels-destroy-your-conversion-rate/"/>
    <id>http://torspark.com/why-carousels-destroy-your-conversion-rate/</id>
    <published>2015-02-09T22:24:00-06:00</published>
    <updated>2015-02-11T16:53:55-06:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Tania Lyerly</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Slideshows, carousels, and rotating offers. Three names for the same thing:
conversion killer!  A lot of homepages have carousels. Marketers and clients of
designers love them because carousels look cool. They let you get a lot more
information on...&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Slideshows, carousels, and rotating offers. Three names for the same thing:
conversion killer!  A lot of homepages have carousels. Marketers and clients of
designers love them because carousels look cool. They let you get a lot more
information on your homepage, and you don’t have to decide which is most
important. If carousels are so cool and popular, why do &lt;strong&gt;your sales funnel and
bottom line hate carousels&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Key Reasons Why Carousels Kill Your Conversion Rate&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Low user engagement&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Low click-through rate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Positioning overrules great content&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Usability sucks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Banner blindness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Carousels have low levels of user engagement and click-through rates&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes carousels look pretty, but people don’t engage with them. Don’t believe me?
Erik Runyon proved it. (He’s the Director of Web Communications at the
University of Notre Dame. He’s also a web developer.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Erik tracked user engagement of carousels on four of Notre Dame’s websites. His
findings: &lt;strong&gt;1% of visitors clicked on the carousel&lt;/strong&gt;. To put that in
perspective, if you have 100,000 visitors to your website, only 1,000 will click
on the carousel. And there’s more!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking a closer look at the features in positions 2-5 in the carousels, they
range from approximately 3% in position 2 to 2.6% in position 5. &lt;strong&gt;Less than 3%
of 1% of visitors clicked through a carousel.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="ND.edu Feature Click-through Rates
graph" src="/img/ndedu-carousel-click-through-rates.png" /&gt;
&lt;a href="http://erikrunyon.com/2013/07/carousel-interaction-stats/"&gt;image credit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you had 100,000 visitors that 3% of 1% represents ONLY 30 visitors. That’s a
pretty terrible click-through rate! Instead what matters is the position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Position 1 Has the Highest Conversions, but You May Be Leaving Conversions on the Table&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe you’re thinking, “What if we rotate what is in the first position? Then we
don’t have to worry about click-through rates.” From a usability stand-point,
this is an awful idea (more explanation on that in a bit). Erik tracked this
too. Here’s what he found (site 4 in red is the auto-rotate).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Feature Click-through Rates Multiple Sites
graph" src="/img/ndedu-carousel-click-through-rates-sites.png" /&gt;
&lt;a href="http://erikrunyon.com/2013/01/carousel-stats/"&gt;image credit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, whatever is shown in &lt;strong&gt;position one always has the highest conversion
rate regardless of the message&lt;/strong&gt;. The reason is position one receives the most
traffic views and interaction (being first and all that). If the message in
position one is not your most compelling message, then you are losing out on
conversions and revenue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="/catalyst/"&gt;A/B testing&lt;/a&gt; can help you determine your best message&lt;/strong&gt; so you
don&amp;rsquo;t leave conversions and money on the table.  Here’s an example of how A/B
testing could improve your conversion rate (or carousel, though we generally
recommend not using carousels in the first place):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say you sell watches. You have three watches that are the same except for
color: silver, blue, and black. You decide to have a carousel that shows each of
the three watches in that order (silver, blue, and black).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know from Erik’s study that the silver watch will receive the most traffic
engagement. It will appear to have the highest conversion rate because of its
position. However, had you A/B tested each of the watches individually your
conversion rates change. For the sake of the example, say you found that the
silver watch had a conversion rate of 10%, the blue 5%, and the black 20%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meaning the black watch, if it was in position 1, would double your conversions.
Instead, the black watch is barely generating you any conversions hidden away in
position 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The top of your homepage is prime real estate! You should have one focused
message that maximizes visitor engagement. (If you aren’t sure on the best
message, A/B test it.) The last thing you want to do is frustrate your visitors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Carousels Frustrate and Annoy Visitors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Guy punching laptop" src="/img/guy-punching-laptop.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usability for carousels sucks!  And auto-rotating carousels are the worst of the
worst. Here’s why:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some carousels auto-rotate and there is no navigation options for the user.
Meaning if your visitor sees something they like and misses it, they have to
wait through the whole slideshow again. Seriously?!? Who wants to do that? I’ll
tell you who, nobody.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Visitors are less likely to generate a conversion when frustrated or
annoyed.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, what if your user misses the content that was relevant to them? They may
not even realize they missed something. The Neilsen Norman Group did a usability
study on auto-forwarding carousels. They found that the user was given the task:
&lt;em&gt;“Does Siemens have any special deals on washing machines?”&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;The user failed
the task to find the needed information because the panel auto-rotated&lt;/strong&gt; instead
of staying still.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, even if you give your visitors navigation controls, everyone reads at
different speeds. It’s annoying to have content change when you are in the
middle of reading it. Or you have to wait for it to change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As discussed previously, carousels that don’t auto-rotate will depend on
position strength to generate conversions. This is of course assuming your
visitors aren’t ignoring your carousel in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Visitors are Ignoring Your Carousel ON PURPOSE!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s called banner blindness. Consciously or subconsciously visitors are
ignoring your carousels because they are mistaking them for an advertisement.
(They look like banners.) Remember Erik Runyon’s research? 99% of visitors were
NOT interacting with the carousel. Some visitors may have not found the content
relevant, but a large number were probably just ignoring the carousel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider this statistic from Solve Media (an advertising consulting company):
you are 475.28 times more likely to survive a plane crash than you are to click
on a banner ad. Meaning, if your visitors consciously or subconsciously think
your carousel is an ad, it is going to get ignored. &lt;strong&gt;Your most important
content is being ignored because it is in a carousel.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Alternatives to using a Carousel&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point we are in agreement: carousels look cool but kill your conversion
rate. So what other options do you have?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kill the carousel and replace it with &lt;strong&gt;one main, focused message&lt;/strong&gt;. If you
aren’t sure which your best message is, A/B test it. (&lt;a href="/catalyst/"&gt;We can help you with
that&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another option is to &lt;strong&gt;replace the carousel with a user self-identified
persona&lt;/strong&gt; like vitamintalent.com does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Sceenshot of vitamintalent.com" src="/img/vitamin-talent-screenshot.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clicking “Hire Talent” vs “Looking for work?” directs the user to the most
relevant part of the site for them. (Also notice the singular focused message!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on your business, &lt;strong&gt;replace the carousel with a video&lt;/strong&gt;. It could be
demoing a product or a relevant how-to video. Video content is a great addition
to your site to help improve conversions. As an added bonus, video content will
help your SEO rankings! Google ranks websites with video content higher than
those without.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could also &lt;strong&gt;replace the carousel with a call-to-action or sign-up form&lt;/strong&gt;.
No place on your website is more visible than the top of your homepage. It is
prime real-estate. A strong call-to-action or sign-up form here that resonates
with your visitors can give your conversion rate a healthy boost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;If You Must Use a Carousel…&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are times when a carousel is useful. But you should be careful when,
where, and how they are used. Portfolios, a gallery of photographs, or any
product that is very visually oriented are perfect examples. (Think about the
real-estate industry or fashion/jewelry industries.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Carousels should appear below the fold and contain non-vital content.&lt;/strong&gt; You
should not rely on a carousel as the primary delivery option for your most
important content. Instead the carousel should complement your homepage content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make the carousel navigation obvious and 100% user controlled.&lt;/strong&gt; Slower and
international readers will thank you. In fact all of your visitors will thank
you for returning the power to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use no more than 3-4 slides on your carousel.&lt;/strong&gt; The click-through rate is very
low at this point. The chances of slides in position four and later being viewed
are diminutive. (Really, the chances of slides after position one being viewed
at all are small.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a select few circumstances, a carousel can be a beneficial addition to your
homepage or website. However, most businesses don’t fall under those
circumstances. Instead, their carousels are killing their conversions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your site has a carousel, send whoever needs convincing a &lt;a href="/why-carousels-destroy-your-conversion-rate/"&gt;link to this
page&lt;/a&gt; before that carousel kills
any more of your conversions.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A/B Testing Crash Course: 5 Questions (and Answers) You Need to Know</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://torspark.com/ab-testing-crash-course-5-questions-and-answers-you-need-to-know/"/>
    <id>http://torspark.com/ab-testing-crash-course-5-questions-and-answers-you-need-to-know/</id>
    <published>2015-02-02T22:04:00-06:00</published>
    <updated>2015-02-11T15:04:28-06:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Tania Lyerly</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No Textbook required. Not even a Dictionary.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here at Torspark, we are firm believers in asking lots of questions. With that
in mind, here are the most common questions about A/B testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is A/B testing?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What can A/B testing do for your business...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No Textbook required. Not even a Dictionary.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here at Torspark, we are firm believers in asking lots of questions. With that
in mind, here are the most common questions about A/B testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is A/B testing?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What can A/B testing do for your business?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How does A/B testing work?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do you pick the winner of an A/B test?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How long should you run an A/B test?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bonus Question: What do all of those marketing sales-y speak headlines &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt;
mean?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A straightforward bundle of questions to ask, but the &lt;strong&gt;answers are a different
matter&lt;/strong&gt;. The answers tend to be made more complicated than they should be from a
combination of technical terms and sales-y marketing speak. This is why we
decided to answer these questions, minus the dictionary, textbook, or marketing
translator to understand. Here we go!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;1. What is A/B testing?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A/B testing (or split testing) is when you &lt;strong&gt;test two variations&lt;/strong&gt; of something to
see &lt;strong&gt;which performs better&lt;/strong&gt;. Usually you test a new version (B) that you think
could do better against the control version (A). Or if you don’t have a control
version, you could just start testing both alternatives against each other right
away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can test more than two variations as well. A three variation split test
would be known as an A/B/C test. One letter is assigned for each variation, and
you could continue on with four or more variations in this manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;2. What can A/B testing do for your business?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The primary use for A/B testing is to &lt;strong&gt;gather conversion data&lt;/strong&gt;. To understand the
importance of conversion data, let’s talk about data and sales funnels for a
second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have enough data, you can construct the flow of your sales funnel. This
means determining where your traffic is coming from, how many people are
clicking through your website, how many people end up &lt;strong&gt;buying your product&lt;/strong&gt; or
service, and what path they took to get there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, even the best sales funnels leak. Holes in your funnel are &lt;strong&gt;where people
drop off&lt;/strong&gt; at each stage. By seeing the big picture painted by the data, you can
figure out where the leaks are. Once you know where the barriers to conversion
are, you can start to fix them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fix can be anything from better headlines and copy to adding (or removing)
videos. Sometimes it’s even as simple as changing the color of a button. It
really just &lt;strong&gt;depends on your customers&lt;/strong&gt; and what they respond to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where A/B testing comes into play. It is used to test those fixes to
your leaking sales funnel. By A/B testing the fix, you can determine if your fix
&lt;strong&gt;actually works&lt;/strong&gt;. Or if your fix made your sales funnel leak some more. Or if it
didn’t make a difference either way. Some fixes will have a greater improvement
than others, while sometimes you will need a combination of fixes to see an
improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With some trial and error, you can &lt;strong&gt;find the right combination to optimize
conversions&lt;/strong&gt; and minimize leaks in your sales funnel. The right boost to your
conversion rate should &lt;strong&gt;increase your revenue&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you understand the theory for A/B testing, but what does this look like with
some real numbers? Don&amp;rsquo;t worry, you won&amp;rsquo;t need a calculator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Scientific Calculator and Stats Book" src="/img/scientific-calculator.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say you have a business selling some software. Your current conversion
rate is 10%, and your yearly revenue is $500,000. Your business then conducts
several A/B tests to optimize conversions in your sales funnel (without changing
prices). As a result, you were able to increase your total overall conversion
rate by 3%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You new total conversion rate is now 13% (10% original + 3% improvement = 13%).
That extra 3% increase in your total conversion rate represents an additional
$15,000 in &lt;strong&gt;yearly revenue&lt;/strong&gt; for your business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not a bad chunk of change for running a few tests. Especially when you consider
that your business will get this extra $15,000 &lt;em&gt;every year&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if your business was able to continue to optimize your conversions
overtime? So that 3% increase became 5% or 7% as different tests improved
different aspects of your sales funnel. Those percentages will compound (just
like compounding interest rates), and revenue will really increase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;3. How does A/B testing work?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say you want to target the number of people signing up for a free demo on
your website. You are worried you are missing out on conversions because you
think people &lt;em&gt;aren’t noticing&lt;/em&gt; the bland button that blends into the background.
You decide to perform an A/B test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="A/B testing gray button vs orange button" src="/img/ab-test-gray-orange-button.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original button is version “A” and the new bright orange button is version
“B”. Half of your traffic to the website will see version “A” and half will see
version “B”. Some tools will declare the winning version based on the higher
conversion rate after a set amount of time or visitors. They’ll even
automatically apply the changes as soon as they pick a winner. This &lt;strong&gt;is not&lt;/strong&gt; how
you want to declare a test winner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;4. How do you pick the winner of an A/B test?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Excited Kids with Laptop" src="/img/excited-kids.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Declaring a winner sounds simple, but it can get a little tricky because of the
multiple factors: sample size, statistical significance, and getting an &lt;strong&gt;accurate
representation of your business traffic&lt;/strong&gt;. (Wait, don’t grab your textbook yet!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statistical significance is when a statistic is deemed reliable. So a test with
a 95% statistical significance means there is &lt;strong&gt;less than a 5% chance&lt;/strong&gt; that the
results of the test could be due to &lt;em&gt;random chance&lt;/em&gt;. Remember, the higher the
statistical significance percentage, the more you can trust in the results of
your test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To achieve a higher level of statistical significance, you will need to increase
your sample size (the number of people you are testing). You will also need to
increase your sample size the more variations you test. In all honesty, your
sample size can &lt;em&gt;never be too big&lt;/em&gt;. This is where time and money become factors,
which we’ll explore in the next section. But you will need certain minimums to
achieve statistical significance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sample size and statistical significance alone are &lt;strong&gt;not enough&lt;/strong&gt; to declare a
winner when making business decisions. Your test should run long enough for your
sample size to &lt;strong&gt;accurately represent&lt;/strong&gt; your business traffic. These elements
combined together help you decide how long to run the test for and eventually
for declaring the winner and &lt;strong&gt;making the right decision&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;5. How long should you run an A/B test?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The very simple statistical answer is once a test has reached statistical
significance then the test is complete, but that isn’t entirely accurate when
&lt;strong&gt;trying to make an informed decision&lt;/strong&gt;. It is at best a half answer and very
misleading at worst. You want to achieve a combination of a high level of
statistical significance that is indicative of your conversion funnel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider this&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if you get all of the traffic you need for statistical significance in an
hour? Is that one hour’s worth of traffic truly representative of all your
business traffic? Maybe yes… maybe no… But the only way you can be certain is to
let the test continue to run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you declare a winner that is statistically significant but is &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt;
representative of your business traffic, you could be implementing a change that
actually hurts your business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going back to our version “A” gray button and version “B” orange button, let’s
say version “A” reaches statistical significance in one hour. If you peek at the
results early, you may see “A” as being the winner. However, if you let the test
continue to run, you’d end up with version “B” having a higher conversion rate
in the longer term with a larger sample size. In this scenario, the traffic in
the one hour was &lt;strong&gt;not indicative&lt;/strong&gt; of the larger conversion funnel trend where
version “B” was the true winner. This is why you shouldn&amp;rsquo;t peek at ongoing
tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This gets us back to the original question of how long to run a test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We recommend that A/B tests should be run through &lt;strong&gt;a minimum of two online
business cycles&lt;/strong&gt;. This helps to minimize the chance of anomalies and false
positives in the data. In theory, the data that comes from those two business
cycles should look pretty similar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How long is your online business cycle? An online business cycle usually ranges
from &lt;strong&gt;one to four weeks&lt;/strong&gt;, but will vary from business to business. It depends on
your consistent activities for &lt;strong&gt;driving traffic&lt;/strong&gt; to your business, but we’ll dive
into that another time. (If you’d like help figuring out your online business
cycle, just &lt;a href="mailto:3wojkp7a"&gt;shoot us an email&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you make the front page of a major site like &lt;a href="http://techcrunch.com"&gt;Tech
Crunch&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.reddit.com"&gt;reddit&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/"&gt;Hacker
News&lt;/a&gt; and get an &lt;em&gt;abnormal&lt;/em&gt; spike in traffic during
one cycle, be cautious when making any decisions. Ask yourself if that traffic
really represents your usual business. You should consider running the test even
longer to balance things out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this ladies and gentlemen is how a statistical answer to a business scenario
can be both correct &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; incorrect at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you have a basic understanding of A/B testing. So let’s spice things up a
little bit and get fancy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;6. Bonus Question: What do all of those marketing sales-y speak headlines &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; mean?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You think you have a handle on this A/B testing thing and then you come across a
headline like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&amp;ldquo;We’ll &lt;strong&gt;increase your conversions&lt;/strong&gt; by 30%!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Fancy Marketer&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That sounds great. Where do I sign up?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have probably seen similar sales-y headlines elsewhere. Maybe you are
thinking about that 3% increase in conversion rate earlier. The headline says
30%. Done!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;….&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wait a second… Take a closer look at that headline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It says “increase your conversions &lt;em&gt;by&lt;/em&gt;” a certain percentage.  Why is this one
word such a big deal?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time to break down the sales and marketing speak and understand what those
numbers &lt;em&gt;truly&lt;/em&gt; mean. Because the numbers &lt;em&gt;sound&lt;/em&gt; great, but they may not mean
what you think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Example:
Let’s again say you’re selling some software and your current conversion rate is
10%. We’ll go big with a 30% increase, improvement, or 
&lt;span data-tooltip aria-haspopup="true" class="has-tip" title="more fancy marketing speak"&gt;lift&lt;/span&gt;
on that original 10%. This actually means a &lt;em&gt;true&lt;/em&gt; 3% increase to your original
conversion rate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s &lt;strong&gt;how it works&lt;/strong&gt;. The 30% is applied to the 10% conversion rate, NOT the
total overall conversion rate. 30% of 10% is 3%. (Here’s how the math works
(.3) * (.1) = .03 or 3%.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In layman’s terms, a 30% increase means your old conversion rate of 10% is now
13%. Huh… that 30% seems a little misleading now, doesn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before you get too disappointed, as discussed before, a 3% increase to your
total conversion rate can be a huge &lt;strong&gt;boost to your revenue&lt;/strong&gt;. The best part is as
long as you have the traffic, your testing options to &lt;strong&gt;optimize your sales funnel&lt;/strong&gt;
are endless! The more leaks you patch and barriers you remove to conversions in
your sales funnel, the more you will increase your revenue. A/B testing can
help get you there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: you also need to remember that a 3% improvement in your conversion rate
doesn’t help much if you had to cut your prices in half to get it… But, that’s
for another article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frankly, we love using A/B testing to optimize conversion funnels. Why? Because
&lt;strong&gt;little changes&lt;/strong&gt; can have &lt;strong&gt;big results&lt;/strong&gt;, big changes can have even bigger results,
and they all compound together!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;What’s your next step? What are you going to test? We’d love to &lt;a href="mailto:3wojkp7a"&gt;hear about it&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have a question about what you just read, a question about something else
related to A/B testing, or just want to say hello? &lt;a href="mailto:3wojkp7a"&gt;Shoot us an email&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How to Update Fork from Original Github Repo</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://torspark.com/how-to-update-fork-from-original-github-repo/"/>
    <id>http://torspark.com/how-to-update-fork-from-original-github-repo/</id>
    <published>2014-11-02T19:27:00-06:00</published>
    <updated>2015-01-22T23:07:06-06:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Chris Olds</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;What do you do when you have a custom fork of a repository, and the original
version has some new update that you&amp;rsquo;d like to include in your fork without
losing your customizations? It&amp;rsquo;s a pretty simple process if you just follow the
steps below.
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;What do you do when you have a custom fork of a repository, and the original
version has some new update that you&amp;rsquo;d like to include in your fork without
losing your customizations? It&amp;rsquo;s a pretty simple process if you just follow the
steps below.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Add the original repo&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, you need to &lt;strong&gt;add the parent repo as a second remote&lt;/strong&gt; for your local
fork. You could name this remote after the original owner (ex: torspark), but I
like to name it &amp;ldquo;parent&amp;rdquo; to keep things simple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight shell"&gt;&lt;table style="border-spacing: 0"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="gutter gl" style="text-align: right"&gt;&lt;pre class="lineno"&gt;1&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="code"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;git remote add parent &amp;lt;url-to-parent-repo&amp;gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, I recently made a couple customizations to the
&lt;a href="http://rubygems.org/gems/middleman-spellcheck"&gt;middleman-spellcheck gem&lt;/a&gt;.
This started as a pull request to fix a bug, but then I added a little extra
functionality while I was digging into the code.  Anyway, after my pull request
was accepted, I wanted to update my fork to be based on the current version.
Here&amp;rsquo;s what I typed into my terminal:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight shell"&gt;&lt;table style="border-spacing: 0"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="gutter gl" style="text-align: right"&gt;&lt;pre class="lineno"&gt;1&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="code"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;git remote add parent git@github.com:minivan/middleman-spellcheck.git
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Verify that your remote was added by running:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight shell"&gt;&lt;table style="border-spacing: 0"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="gutter gl" style="text-align: right"&gt;&lt;pre class="lineno"&gt;1&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="code"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;git remote
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Fetch the original repo&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, you can &lt;strong&gt;fetch all the changes&lt;/strong&gt; from the original repo by typing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight shell"&gt;&lt;table style="border-spacing: 0"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="gutter gl" style="text-align: right"&gt;&lt;pre class="lineno"&gt;1&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="code"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;git fetch parent
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will give you a new branch called parent/master. If you&amp;rsquo;re looking for a
specific branch on the parent repository, the following command with list all
branches available, including both those from your fork and the parent repo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight shell"&gt;&lt;table style="border-spacing: 0"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="gutter gl" style="text-align: right"&gt;&lt;pre class="lineno"&gt;1&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="code"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;git branch -a
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Merge or Rebase&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, you just have to either merge or &lt;strong&gt;rebase your branch&lt;/strong&gt; with the parent
repo. If you prefer to merge, checkout your branch, and merge the branch you
want from the parent repo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight shell"&gt;&lt;table style="border-spacing: 0"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="gutter gl" style="text-align: right"&gt;&lt;pre class="lineno"&gt;1
2&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="code"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;git checkout master
git merge parent/master
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, if you&amp;rsquo;re a fan of rebasing code, you can run this instead:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight shell"&gt;&lt;table style="border-spacing: 0"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="gutter gl" style="text-align: right"&gt;&lt;pre class="lineno"&gt;1&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="code"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;git rebase parent/master
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was the only one using my fork at the time, so I chose to rebase in order to
have a cleaner version history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s all there is to it. The features I added have since been pulled into the
original repo, so you can see that
&lt;a href="https://github.com/torspark/middleman-spellcheck"&gt;my fork&lt;/a&gt;
matches the
&lt;a href="https://github.com/minivan/middleman-spellcheck"&gt;original repo&lt;/a&gt; (as of version
0.7.5). This process will make it easy for me to continue adding new feature
branches to my fork while staying current with the original repository as more
pull requests are accepted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What repositories have you contributed to lately? I&amp;rsquo;d love to
&lt;a href="mailto:3wojkp7a"&gt;hear about it&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How to Calculate Article Reading Time with a Custom Middleman Extension</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://torspark.com/how-to-calculate-article-reading-time-with-a-custom-middleman-extension/"/>
    <id>http://torspark.com/how-to-calculate-article-reading-time-with-a-custom-middleman-extension/</id>
    <published>2014-10-20T21:58:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2015-01-22T23:09:10-06:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Chris Olds</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is a quick how-to guide on implementing an estimated reading time feature
for your &lt;a href="http://middlemanapp.com"&gt;Middleman&lt;/a&gt; blog with a custom Middleman
extension.
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is a quick how-to guide on implementing an estimated reading time feature
for your &lt;a href="http://middlemanapp.com"&gt;Middleman&lt;/a&gt; blog with a custom Middleman
extension.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Write the custom extension&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can just drop the code below into the main directory for your Middleman
project. Mine is under &lt;code&gt;torspark.com/reading_time.rb&lt;/code&gt;. Note that this is above
the &lt;code&gt;/source&lt;/code&gt; directory where most of your work will go in a Middleman project.
You could also put it in a top level &lt;code&gt;/extensions&lt;/code&gt; directory alongside the
&lt;code&gt;/source&lt;/code&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;code&gt;/build&lt;/code&gt; directories if you plan to write a lot of custom
extensions. I don&amp;rsquo;t have a need for this yet, so I just left it as an individual
file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight ruby"&gt;&lt;table style="border-spacing: 0"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="gutter gl" style="text-align: right"&gt;&lt;pre class="lineno"&gt;1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10
11
12
13
14
15
16
17
18
19
20
21&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="code"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Outputs the reading time&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# ex: Read this in "about 3 minutes"&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nc"&gt;ReadingTime&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="no"&gt;Middleman&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="no"&gt;Extension&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;initialize&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;app&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;options_hash&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;{},&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;block&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;super&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="k"&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class="n"&gt;helpers&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;reading_time&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;input&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="n"&gt;words_per_minute&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;180&lt;/span&gt;

      &lt;span class="n"&gt;words&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;input&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;split&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;size&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="n"&gt;minutes&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;words&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="sr"&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;/&lt;span class="sr"&gt;words_per_minute).floor
      minutes_label = minutes === 1 ? ' minute' : ' minutes'
      minutes &amp;gt; 0 ? "about &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;#{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;minutes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="sr"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;#{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;minutes_label&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="sr"&gt;" : 'less than 1 minute'
    end
  end
end

::Middleman::Extensions.register(:reading_time, ReadingTime)
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can easily customize line #11 to match the average reading speed for your
readers. &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Words_per_minute"&gt;180 words per minute&lt;/a&gt;
is a conservative estimate for proofreading on a monitor. The average adult can
read between 250 to 300 words per minute. Most of my articles are at least a
little technical, so I decided to stick with 180 wpm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lines #13&amp;ndash;16 calculate the total number of words in the article, and then
pluralize the label if necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last line registers the extension so you can activate it in the &lt;code&gt;config.rb&lt;/code&gt;
file, like the code below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Activate &amp;amp; use your extension&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight ruby"&gt;&lt;table style="border-spacing: 0"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="gutter gl" style="text-align: right"&gt;&lt;pre class="lineno"&gt;1
2&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="code"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;require&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;'reading_time'&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;activate&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;reading_time&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, we just need to use the helper in our layout. The estimated reading times
you can see on
&lt;a title="Build Better Software, Faster" href="http://torspark.com"&gt;Torspark&amp;rsquo;s home page&lt;/a&gt;
and in the upper right of this page (assuming I haven&amp;rsquo;t redesigned things&amp;hellip;)
are generated with the code below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight ruby"&gt;&lt;table style="border-spacing: 0"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="gutter gl" style="text-align: right"&gt;&lt;pre class="lineno"&gt;1
2
3
4
5
6
7&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="code"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# links on source/index.html.haml:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;link_to&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;"Read this article in &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;#{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;reading_time&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;article&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;body&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;article&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Estimated reading time in source/layouts/article.haml:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;p&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="no"&gt;Read&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;this&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;article&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;reading_time&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;current_article&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;body&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Alternative&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For something this simple, you could just drop lines #10&amp;ndash;17 from the first code
block above into the helper section of your Middleman &lt;code&gt;config.rb&lt;/code&gt; file. I went
ahead and built out the full extension, because I&amp;rsquo;m planning to flesh it out a
little more. The separate file also makes things a little cleaner to manage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Feedback? Questions?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s all there is to writing and using your own custom extension for
Middleman. I hope it helps you customize your site. I&amp;rsquo;d love to hear about the
custom extensions you use. &lt;a href="mailto:3wojkp7a"&gt;Drop me a line&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Should I make a gem for you?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I&amp;rsquo;d consider building this out a little more and making a gem if you&amp;rsquo;re
interested. &lt;a href="mailto:3wojkp7a"&gt;Let me know&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Benefits of Weekly Billing for Clients</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://torspark.com/benefits-of-weekly-billing-for-clients/"/>
    <id>http://torspark.com/benefits-of-weekly-billing-for-clients/</id>
    <published>2014-10-17T18:02:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2014-10-28T01:32:32-05:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Chris Olds</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Do you really want to pay 50% up front for your project, before you&amp;rsquo;ve even had
a chance to build a rapport with your developer? Is it a pain to get upper
management to approve that big down payment? Or are you having trouble tracking
&amp;amp; budgeting for various hourly invoices? You&amp;rsquo;re a good client, of course, but do
you want your consultant wasting his time trying to collect fees from other less
reputable clients?
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Do you really want to pay 50% up front for your project, before you&amp;rsquo;ve even had
a chance to build a rapport with your developer? Is it a pain to get upper
management to approve that big down payment? Or are you having trouble tracking
&amp;amp; budgeting for various hourly invoices? You&amp;rsquo;re a good client, of course, but do
you want your consultant wasting his time trying to collect fees from other less
reputable clients?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe the developer you hired turned out to be a hack. Or your dev just doesn&amp;rsquo;t
seem to have enough time for you. Or they don&amp;rsquo;t communicate with you as much as
you&amp;rsquo;d like. Whatever the reason, now you&amp;rsquo;re wondering how you can salvage some
of that hefty down payment or if you just have to try to make the most of the
situation. It may seem a little scary at first, but up front weekly billing can
help you avoid these situations. See the benefits below, or read about
&lt;a title="Charging weekly will make you happier" href="/advantages-of-weekly-billing-for-developers/"&gt;weekly billing from a developer&amp;rsquo;s perspective&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Why you should want to be charged weekly as a client&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Easy on your budget&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Weekly payments are easy to budget.&lt;/strong&gt; You know exactly how much you&amp;rsquo;ll need to
pay each week. A lot of managers can even just use their discretionary fund to
pay for development, rather than having to get a 50% down payment approved by
upper management. If you&amp;rsquo;re a small business, you can easily make payments with
your credit card, and not worry about a large upfront payment putting your
business at risk by becoming cash poor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Limit your risk&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By paying weekly, you can &lt;strong&gt;limit the risk&lt;/strong&gt; of getting stuck with a bad
developer. If you aren&amp;rsquo;t satisfied with the past week&amp;rsquo;s worth of work, you are
free to stop paying and find a new developer. No need to feel like you&amp;rsquo;re
committed to a slow developer. No need to worry about how to get the most out of
your down payment or even trying to recoup some of it in court. At worst, you&amp;rsquo;re
out just a week&amp;rsquo;s worth of money, and that&amp;rsquo;s it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Know your developer is focused on your project&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By paying your developer for a week&amp;rsquo;s worth of work in advance, you can be
secure in the knowledge that &lt;strong&gt;your developer is focused on your project&lt;/strong&gt;. You
don&amp;rsquo;t really want them working on your project for a couple hours here and there
among the other projects on their plate. That just slows the development down
and decreases the quality, because of all the context switching they&amp;rsquo;re going
through, bouncing from project to project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;ll also get the added benefit of having a &lt;strong&gt;faster and more motivated
developer&lt;/strong&gt;. If you&amp;rsquo;re paying hourly invoices, the slower your dev works, the
more money they&amp;rsquo;ll receive. Is that right? Your developer should be an expert
professional. If they know you trust them to provide value, they&amp;rsquo;ll be
encouraged to work as efficiently as possible, because procrastinating won&amp;rsquo;t
make them any more money. There&amp;rsquo;s also the push to deliver value &lt;em&gt;every single
week&lt;/em&gt;, because they know you could choose to just end the engagement at any
time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Why waste your time arguing over what&amp;rsquo;s in scope&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paying weekly means you don&amp;rsquo;t have to constantly check the original scope
document to see if you can request this or that little change. Let&amp;rsquo;s face it,
that scope document is usually out of date &lt;em&gt;within a week&lt;/em&gt; of signing it. You
won&amp;rsquo;t have to waste time on addendums to the original contract, because you can
just as for the change, knowing that you&amp;rsquo;ve already paid for this week&amp;rsquo;s work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, weekly billing doesn&amp;rsquo;t sound so scary does it? If you give it a chance, I
bet you&amp;rsquo;ll even prefer it. If your developer isn&amp;rsquo;t charging weekly, maybe you
should ask them why not? You could send them a link to the
&lt;a title="The best way to charge as a consultant" href="/advantages-of-weekly-billing-for-developers/"&gt;advantages of weekly billing for consultants&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
