<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Torspark</title>
  <subtitle>Custom Software Development &amp; Consultancy</subtitle>
  <id>http://torspark.com</id>
  <link href="http://torspark.com"/>
  <link href="http://torspark.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2015-04-17T11:58:00-05:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Chris Olds</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Mobile-Friendly vs Mobile-Optimization vs Responsive Design for Websites</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://torspark.com/mobile-friendly-vs-mobile-optimized-vs-responsive-design/"/>
    <id>http://torspark.com/mobile-friendly-vs-mobile-optimized-vs-responsive-design/</id>
    <published>2015-04-17T11:58:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2015-05-11T16:26:29-05:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Tania Lyerly</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I get a lot of questions about the differences between mobile-friendly vs
mobile-optimization vs responsive design for websites. These questions include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is a mobile-friendly website?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is mobile-optimization?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is responsive design?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I get a lot of questions about the differences between mobile-friendly vs
mobile-optimization vs responsive design for websites. These questions include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is a mobile-friendly website?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is mobile-optimization?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is responsive design?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the differences of all of the above?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where does mobile first design fit in?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the best design strategy for my website?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My goal is to answer all of these questions, plus a few more along the way. (If
you’d like a deeper explanation, or have other questions you’d like answered,
just &lt;a href="mailto:%203wojkp7a"&gt;shoot me an email!&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For clarity’s sake, when I say mobile or mobile device, I am referring to
devices that are the approximate size and shape of most smartphones (mobile
phones).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, let’s hop to it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Mobile-Friendly Websites&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google’s search rankings now emphasize and &lt;a href="/google-announcement-mobile-friendly/"&gt;reward mobile-friendly
websites&lt;/a&gt;. Many people may think that
having a mobile-friendly website is good enough, and for Google’s robots it is!
But this is not necessarily good enough for the visitors coming to your
website. In short, &lt;strong&gt;mobile-friendly is the bare minimum&lt;/strong&gt; mobile design
strategy you should have for your mobile visitors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you aren’t sure if your website is mobile-friendly, then check-out Google’s
&lt;a href="https://www.google.com/webmasters/tools/mobile-friendly/"&gt;webmaster tool&lt;/a&gt;. A
mobile-friendly website is often just a slimmed down version of the website
viewed on a desktop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, as a general rule your content should be written in at least 14 or
16 pt font. It seems big, but when it gets shrunk down anything less will be
hard to read. Hard to read ≠ mobile-friendly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mobile-friendly websites will work for mobile users, but these websites were
designed for the desktop users.&lt;/strong&gt; A smaller version of your desktop website can
be functional but may not be as user friendly as it could be&amp;hellip; And this is
where mobile-optimization starts to enter the fray.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Mobile-Optimized Websites&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="using mobile device" src="/img/mobile-use.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All mobile-optimized websites are mobile-friendly, but not all mobile-friendly
websites are mobile-optimized. Mobile-optimization targets mobile users; these
websites are designed for smaller screens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A mobile-optimized website will reformat itself for mobile users&lt;/strong&gt;. It is not
just a shrunken down version of the desktop website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Design features of a mobile-optimized website can include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Single column layout&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easy, simple navigation that is “thumb friendly”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Large graphics with white-space borders for those of us with large or clumsy fingers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Formatted content for maximum readability&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Limited to no need for typing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Image file sizes are smaller for the mobile version of the website than those used for the desktop version of the website. (This allows for quicker load times.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A fewer number of features overall (minimalist, uncluttered design)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mobile users are much more likely to be searching for a quick answer&lt;/strong&gt;
compared to their desktop search counterparts. (I tend to search for
restaurants, movie reviews, and directions on my phone. I am not doing in-depth
searches on my phone on technical topics like mobile-optimized design. I save
those types of searches for my laptop.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of a mobile-optimized website is to &lt;strong&gt;make the website as
frictionless as possible for the mobile user&lt;/strong&gt;. Mobile users are seeking the
quickest, most efficient way to answer their questions. Mobile-optimization
aims to do exactly that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Websites Created with Responsive Design&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="tablet sitting on laptop" src="/img/tablet.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Responsively designed websites do exactly as phrase suggest. They “respond” to
the screen size of the device being used. In a sense, responsive design picks
up where mobile-optimization leaves off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Responsive design reformats and restructures websites for &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt;
device&amp;mdash;regardless of screen size.&lt;/strong&gt; Mobile-optimization only does this for
mobile devices. With responsive design, the layout of the website will scale
from the smaller screens of mobile, tablets, and small laptops, to the standard
desktop screen and even larger widescreen monitors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Responsive design offers flexibility and great usability on all devices for
users. It’s really the only way to guarantee that your website will look good
and have optimized usability on any device.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are curious, Torspark is a responsively designed website. (Try looking
at the &lt;a href="/"&gt;homepage&lt;/a&gt;, or any other part of our website on different devices.
When you do, you’ll see a different, scaled version for each device type. Or,
just resize your browser and see how everything balances out on the page.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Mobile-First Design Strategy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mobile-first is a design strategy in which &lt;strong&gt;the mobile version of the website
is designed first over the traditional desktop version&lt;/strong&gt;. This design strategy
can also apply to products designed for and marketed to mobile users first,
ahead of “traditional” internet users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of design issues come from trying to stuff too many features into a
single page. When designing with mobile-first in mind, you tend to get a
simpler, cleaner design structure. This works well as a base, because it’s
easier to add relevant features into the desktop view as needed, rather than
trying to stuff every bell and whistle into a mobile view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2014 was &lt;a href="http://www.emarketer.com/Article/Mobile-Will-Account-72-of-US-Digital-Ad-Spend-by-2019/1012258"&gt;the breakout year for mobile
usage&lt;/a&gt;&amp;mdash;the
first year mobile use surpassed daily desktop use. (Adults spent on average 2
hours and 51 minutes on mobile devices daily, but only 2 hours and 12 minutes
daily on desktops.) &lt;strong&gt;Mobile first and responsive design strategies are
becoming more in demand as the trend of increased mobile use continues.&lt;/strong&gt; If
you aren’t sure about jumping into the deep end of responsive design, a mobile
first design strategy can be the first step as part of a larger responsive
design strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What type of design is best for my business and my website?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The not very helpful answer is “it depends”. Honestly, the answer depends on
the answers to the following questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the purpose of your website?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What do you want your website to do for visitors?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What devices are you expecting your visitors to be accessing your site from?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="airport arrival and baggage claim sign" src="/img/airport-arrival.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Websites are meant to take visitors on a digital journey. That journey is
supposed to be as smooth and frictionless as possible. &lt;strong&gt;The easier you can
make navigating your website, the more likely you are to &lt;a href="/catalyst/"&gt;increase
conversions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, what is the budget for your website? Mobile-optimized and responsively
designed websites are often a little more expensive than mobile-friendly
websites. Why? In short, they take longer to develop and build.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the long run, the &lt;strong&gt;extra optimization to functionality and usability
offered by a responsively designed or mobile-optimized site will provide you
with a higher ROI&lt;/strong&gt; than a site that is just mobile-friendly. Now, whether or
not the expense is justified will have to be evaluated on a
business-by-business basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a side note, have you tried to use your business’s website as if you were a
customer? What about as a mobile user? Do you know what your mobile site looks
like? If you are drawing a blank, or have a panicky uncertain feeling right
now, that’s probably not a good indicator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Consider The Following for Mobile-Friendly vs Mobile-Optimized vs Responsive Design&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is your main customer base cruising your website on a desktop? Then maybe a
mobile-friendly website is good enough for you. Google doesn’t penalize you in
the search rankings, and you don’t spend extra money on a mobile-optimized or
responsively designed website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;On the other hand&amp;hellip;&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you have any kind of e-commerce, blogs, or a customer base that actively
uses mobile devices? If this is the case, then you may want to invest in a
mobile-optimized or responsively designed website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Mobile-Optimized and Responsively Designed Websites Can Offer a Creative User Experience&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="taking picture of a building with a mobile device" src="/img/mobile-picture-taking.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just because visitors are viewing your website on a smaller screen, doesn’t
mean your site has to be boring. &lt;strong&gt;Remember mobile users have the ability to
take pictures and videos, make phone calls, use GPS for finding things near
their location, and so much more!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is the beauty of stepping beyond &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; a mobile-friendly website.
There are so many new and different user interface options for visitors NOT
using a desktop. Some businesses even have completely different website
versions for desktop users versus mobile users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think about your visitors. What type of experience do you want them to have
using your website? Optimize your website for that experience!  Given the
possibilities with the internet, saying the sky’s the limit seems almost
diminutive.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Google Announcement: Mobile-Friendly Websites Receive Better Search Rankings</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://torspark.com/google-announcement-mobile-friendly/"/>
    <id>http://torspark.com/google-announcement-mobile-friendly/</id>
    <published>2015-04-05T11:24:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2015-05-11T16:33:47-05:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Tania Lyerly</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Is your website designed to be
&lt;a href="/mobile-friendly-vs-mobile-optimized-vs-responsive-design/"&gt;mobile-friendly&lt;/a&gt;?
If it’s not, you have until April 21st to make some changes. Starting April 21,
2015,
&lt;a href="http://googlewebmastercentral.blogspot.com/2015/02/finding-more-mobile-friendly-search.html"&gt;Google&lt;/a&gt;
is rewarding those websites that are mobile-friendly with better search
rankings.
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Is your website designed to be
&lt;a href="/mobile-friendly-vs-mobile-optimized-vs-responsive-design/"&gt;mobile-friendly&lt;/a&gt;?
If it’s not, you have until April 21st to make some changes. Starting April 21,
2015,
&lt;a href="http://googlewebmastercentral.blogspot.com/2015/02/finding-more-mobile-friendly-search.html"&gt;Google&lt;/a&gt;
is rewarding those websites that are mobile-friendly with better search
rankings.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;How do you know if your website is mobile-friendly?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google has a &lt;a href="https://www.google.com/webmasters/tools/mobile-friendly/"&gt;webmaster
tool&lt;/a&gt; that you can use
to check if your website is mobile-friendly. Just put in your site’s URL and
wait 20-30 seconds while it analyzes your website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;If your website is mobile-friendly, you’ll get something that looks a little like this:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="torspark googlebot mobile view" src="/img/torspark-googlebot-mobile-view.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Congratulations! Your website passed Google’s mobile-friendly test!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, many websites are built with mobile in mind. However, &lt;strong&gt;mobile-friendly
does not mean your site is user-friendly&lt;/strong&gt;. The best sites will be a combination
of mobile-optimized and responsive design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;If your website is not mobile-friendly, then Google will show you something like this:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="idc global googlebot mobile view" src="/img/idc-global-googlebot-mobile-view.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bad news is if your website is not mobile-friendly there isn’t necessarily a
one stop, fix-all solution. How to fix your website primarily depends on how
your website was built, who built it, and who has access to make changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remember to backup your site &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; starting to make any changes!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;How was your website built?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Was your website built using a content management system (CMS)? (Examples of
popular CMSes include WordPress, Joomla, Drupal, and Magento.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your website was built using a CMS, check out Google’s list of &lt;a href="https://developers.google.com/webmasters/mobile-sites/website-software/?hl=en-US#how-do-i-make-my-site-mobile-friendly"&gt;technical
guides&lt;/a&gt;
on various CMSes to making your website mobile friendly. &lt;strong&gt;If you haven’t
installed updates for the theme or templates on your website, that may be all
you need.&lt;/strong&gt; Other problems could be related to the plugins that are installed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OR&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Was your website custom built with a programming language? (A few common
languages used for building websites include Ruby, Python, JavaScript, PHP,
Java, and Perl.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this is the case, then Google’s &lt;a href="https://developers.google.com/webmasters/mobile-sites/mobile-seo/?hl=en-US"&gt;guide on mobile
SEO&lt;/a&gt;
could be helpful to figuring out and solving the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Who built your website, and who has access to make changes?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people build or code their own sites, while others outsource it to a
developer. If you built it yourself, check out the above links. For those of you
working with a developer, Google’s webmaster tools has some &lt;a href="https://developers.google.com/webmasters/mobile-sites/get-started/hire-developer?hl=en-US"&gt;helpful
advice&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if you had a developer build your website on a CMS (like WordPress),
installing updates may be the quick fix you can do yourself. If this is not
something you are comfortable doing, or it doesn’t fix the problem, then talk to
your developer. If your developer can’t or doesn’t know how to fix the problem,
you should find a new developer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once your website is deemed mobile-friendly by Google, your site will be given a
mobile-friendly label. You won’t see this label if you perform a search for your
site on a desktop. This label only appears when searches are performed on a
mobile device.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="mobile-screen-capture-torspark" src="/img/torspark-mobile-friendly-seo.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A mobile-unfriendly website will not completely doom your search rankings. Many
factors go into search rankings, however mobile friendliness does represent a
larger trend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mobile-based searches are only going to continue to increase.&lt;/strong&gt; Traffic will
flock to those websites that are mobile-friendly or mobile-optimized over those
that are not. Less traffic and higher bounce rates from poor usability over time
will hurt your rankings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While a lot of factors go into search rankings, don’t let
mobile-friendliness be a factor that counts against you.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Hierarchy of Optimization for Websites: The Building Blocks of Conversion Rate Optimization</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://torspark.com/hierarchy-of-optimization/"/>
    <id>http://torspark.com/hierarchy-of-optimization/</id>
    <published>2015-03-23T07:24:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2015-03-26T00:43:48-05:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Tania Lyerly</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Many people associate conversion rate optimization (CRO) with &lt;a href="/ab-testing-crash-course-5-questions-and-answers-you-need-to-know/"&gt;A/B
testing&lt;/a&gt; or
other kinds of split testing. Testing is part of CRO, but it is only one facet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wikipedia defines conversion rate optimization as “the method of creating an
experience for...&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Many people associate conversion rate optimization (CRO) with &lt;a href="/ab-testing-crash-course-5-questions-and-answers-you-need-to-know/"&gt;A/B
testing&lt;/a&gt; or
other kinds of split testing. Testing is part of CRO, but it is only one facet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wikipedia defines conversion rate optimization as “the method of creating an
experience for a website or landing page visitor with the goal of increasing
the percentage of visitors that convert into customers”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s a great definition. A long one too! Which leaves you thinking- “where do
I actually start?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The obvious answer is your website. That’s where you want to optimize your
conversions.  But websites have a lot of variation and complexity. This is
where the Hierarchy of Optimization comes into play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Hierarchy of Optimization is the methodology behind conversion rate
optimization. It provides a structured, systematic approach to improving the
performance of your website and your conversions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Model Behind the Methodology&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Hierarchy of Optimization framework is based on 
&lt;a href='#' data-reveal-id='modalMaslow'&gt;Maslow’s Hierarchy of Needs&lt;/a&gt;
pyramid model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like with Maslow’s model, the basic requirements of your website are at
the bottom, while the more sophisticated requirements are on top. Without the
lower levels, your website will not function. It’s important to remember&amp;mdash; &lt;strong&gt;if
your website fails at one level, then the subsequent levels are negatively
impacted and your conversion rate suffers&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The five levels are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Purpose&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Accessible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Usable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Intuitive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Persuasive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are looking for the foundational building blocks to improve your
conversions, or you’re launching/redesigning your website, then you are in the
right place!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, let’s go build a pyramid!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Hierarchy of Optimization Mayan Pyramid" src="/img/hierarchy-of-optimization-mayan-pyramid.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;1. Purpose&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Purpose is at the base of your optimization hierarchy pyramid. Without a
purpose, why even have a website?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;What purpose is your website supposed to fulfill?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are your website’s unique objectives and needs for your business?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are you selling a product or service? Think of websites like Amazon
(e-commerce), Basecamp (project management service), and Salesforce (CRM
product).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are you giving information or educating your customer base? Chili’s and other
restaurants have their menus, nutritional information, locations, pictures, and
other information to interest customers in the restaurant’s food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are you looking for engagement and clicking on ads? Facebook and Youtube both
try to keep users on their sites as long as possible. The longer users are
engaged on the site the more likely a user will click on an ad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some websites may fall into more than one category, like Pandora. They are
engaging their customer base with the music, who also listens to the ads. Or
customers buy the subscription to listen without ads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of your website should be clearly defined. &lt;strong&gt;Clarity is key!&lt;/strong&gt;
Everything on your website will stem from this purpose. &lt;strong&gt;If you don’t know
what you are trying to accomplish with your website, then how can you expect
your visitors to know?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;2. Accessible&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Gate - Do Not Enter" src="/img/gate-do-not-enter.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having a purpose is great, but if your website can’t be accessed then you are
up a creek without a paddle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does your website work?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do all of the features on your website work?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are their functions executable?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example is a shopping cart feature. Is each step of the sales process
executable? This starts with finding or accessing the product on your website.
Then adding the product to the shopping cart. Lastly, checking out and paying
for the product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If your website’s primary purpose is unable to be fulfilled because something
doesn’t work, a user can’t access your website, or find your product, then
nothing else matters.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Website accessibility problems&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;Error 404: page not found&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “Error 404: page not found” is the error that you receive when you have a
broken link, a changed link, or a link that doesn’t actually exist for some
reason. (A common reason for a link that doesn’t exist is a typo in the URL.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The standard 404 error is actually just code that gets spit out by the
server. It’s plain text that a user cannot interact with or be redirected
from.&lt;/strong&gt; Basically, this is as inaccessible as it gets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you change a link, it’s best to set up a 301 redirect (more on that in a
little bit). If you delete a page or link, a custom error 404 page can be a fun
way to help get your user back on track. You can also give suggestions on where
your user might like to go, or just have fun with it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are a Star Wars fan like me, than you’ll love Github’s custom error 404
page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Github 404 page" src="/img/github-404.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;301 redirect&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you change the URL for your page or website, you need to set up a 301
redirect. This tells the search engines (and anyone linking to your old URL)
that your page has permanently changed to a new name or location. &lt;strong&gt;301
redirects are especially important for SEO! They transfer a majority of your
SEO juice (90&amp;ndash;99%) from the old URL page to the new one.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, your SEO ranking may take a slight hit. However, this is much better than
starting with zero SEO juice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Product Accessibility on Your Website&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is your product accessible to your customer base? If a potential customer is
looking for your product or service, how easy is it for them to find it on your
website? Additionally, how easy is it for the customer to move through your
sales funnel to complete the sale?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make your shopping cart easy to find and use. According to Listrak’s 2014
Annual Study of Email Tactics used by the top 1000 Internet Retailers, “74% of
online sales are abandoned before the customer completes the traction”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think about that for a second…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3 out of 4 online sales are not completed.&lt;/strong&gt; How much lost revenue does that
represent for your company? Make your products easy to find and easy to
purchase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t hide your sales cart, let it stand out. If customers need to contact you
directly to make a purchase, make sure your contact information is easily
visible on EVERY page of your site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Lower Levels Versus the Upper Levels&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus far we have covered the two fundamental layers of the pyramid: purpose and
accessibility. Like Maslow’s Hierarchy of Needs, the two lowest layers are the
most basic but most crucial in our Hierarchy of Optimization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without these lower levels, nothing else matters. However, your users won’t
realize this. They only see your website when it’s accessible. It’s only the
three upper levels that your users truly interact with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, let’s keep climbing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;3. Usable&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is your website usable?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe you are thinking&amp;mdash; “Wait a minute. My website works. It’s accessible. Of
course it’s usable!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not so fast. Contrary to popular belief, just because something is functional
does not mean it is usable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Thick Drink with Straw" src="/img/thick-drink-with-straw.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you ever tried to drink a thick milkshake out of a small straw? You aren’t
going to get much of that milkshake any time soon. That straw is functional,
but it’s not very usable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How long does it take for your website to load?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Your website is too easy to use. It’s too fast and too clear to understand.”
&amp;mdash; Said no one EVER!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UX design (user experience design) is your BEST friend when it comes to
designing your website. You want your navigation to be user-friendly. This
starts to overlap with being intuitive (more on that later).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What about mobile responsive design?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is your website designed to work on multiple devices? &lt;strong&gt;Nothing scares off
customers faster than an unusable site.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of being user-friendly is being click-friendly. Here are some of the tools
that we recommend for helping to become more user and click-friendly:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Crazyegg for heatmaps and click maps of your website. Helps you understand
and see where your visitors are looking and clicking.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Usertesting.com for real users telling you what they think about using your
website &lt;em&gt;while&lt;/em&gt; they use it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Squiggle" src="/img/squiggle.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The shortest distance between two points is a straight line. Usability of your
website should be like a straight line, not a squiggle&amp;hellip; Or any other shape
for that matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your visitors should spend their time experiencing whatever the purpose of your
website is. &lt;strong&gt;Visitors should NOT be spending their time trying to figure out
how to use your website.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;4. Intuitive&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Intuitive and usable strongly go hand-in-hand with each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can visitors find what they are looking for when they come to your website?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes? Great! &amp;hellip; Is it where they expected to find it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Your website should feel natural to use. Everything should be where visitors
expect it to be.&lt;/strong&gt; Is the contact information where they expect it? What about
navigating around your website?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There should be a flow to the content and pages on your website.&lt;/strong&gt; It should
be obvious to your visitors where to go and what you want them to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of the buying process, you want to make it as smooth as possible for
your visitors. Most customers do some kind of research before making a
purchase. &lt;strong&gt;Make product reviews, return policies, and the answers to FAQs easy
to find.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider having a portfolio if you sell services like custom printing,
photography, or website design. Could you imagine hiring a photographer without
seeing any of their work?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just this week I saw a website for a company doing web design with no
portfolio. They wanted $1,500 for their web design service. I don’t know about
you, but I’m not inclined to buy from them. If you don’t want to put your
portfolio online, at least tell your visitors that you have samples upon
request.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A demo video showing a product’s benefits and how to use it can also be a great
addition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;People buy from people and companies they trust!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consider what kind of objections a visitor might have to buying or
converting.&lt;/strong&gt; Your website should address these objections, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; do it with as
little usability friction as possible. &lt;strong&gt;Don’t play hide-and-seek with the
answers!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Addressing questions and concerns up front builds trust and confidence in your
company. This in turn will lead to more conversions and sales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this starts to move us into the final step on our pyramid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;5. Persuasive&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Snowcapped Mountain" src="/img/snowcapped-mountain.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The top of the mountain is only the top because it has a whole mountain under
it. At the same time, you can only get to the top of the mountain by climbing
the rest of it. (I guess you could cheat and fly up there, but that’s besides
the point.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Persuasive is the hardest step of the pyramid to get to and to execute. (It’s
all about being on top.) Persuasive also has the greatest impact on your sales
funnel with your visitors. BUT it only counts if you have every layer of the
pyramid before that!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could have the most persuasive copy on your website, but if your website
isn’t  accessible or usable… Welp, you’re out of luck!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Users may not recognize how easy and intuitive your site is, that’s kind of the
point. If your website is not easy to use, then visitors will &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; notice
and won’t stick around for long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Persuasive is where you bring your branding, marketing, and content strategies into play.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each part of your website should have a singular goal that contributes to your
website’s overall purpose. Branding, messaging, and content should all focus on
achieving the singular goals and overarching purpose. Additionally, &lt;strong&gt;any
&lt;a href="/ab-testing-crash-course-5-questions-and-answers-you-need-to-know/"&gt;A/B&lt;/a&gt; or
split testing should have a singular goal that aims to improve your purpose.&lt;/strong&gt;
This clarity will make your website more persuasive to your visitors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going back to intuitive, know the objections or barriers your visitors have
that stop them from buying. If you know these objections, you can
systematically address them in your branding, messaging, and website copy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DO NOT tell your customers what you &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; they want to hear.&lt;/strong&gt; Your
messaging and copy should convey the answers your customers need to hear.
&lt;strong&gt;Talk to your customers, not at them.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you aren’t sure what these objections are, ask them! User polls and surveys
are great ways to get real feedback from your customer base. Also, look at your
competitors. What are they doing that works that you aren’t?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, don’t copy your competitors. &lt;strong&gt;Take what your competitors do well, and
then make it better.&lt;/strong&gt; Be innovative, and think outside of the box. With
technology at their fingertips, users are the smartest they have ever been.
&lt;strong&gt;If you don’t provide the answer or solution to their problem, they will go
elsewhere.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the user doesn’t know they have a problem, educate them. &lt;strong&gt;People tend to
trust people and companies that give them valuable information.&lt;/strong&gt; (Is it
working yet?) As a result, &lt;strong&gt;when users are ready to buy, they will go back to
the people who provided answers and value.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Wrap-Up&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conversion rate optimization is not just about doing one thing or about one
piece. There isn’t a silver bullet. CRO is about how all of the different
pieces come together.The whole is greater than the sum of its parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, knowing where to start with all of the different pieces can be
overwhelming. This is why we have a methodology to serve as a guide on how to
approach conversion rate optimization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you noticed, many of the layers of the pyramid overlapped into each other.
Each layer of the pyramid, is just that - a layer. Take out one layer, and at
best you have a smaller pyramid. At worst your whole pyramid falls apart. Only
when you put all of the layers together properly do you get a pyramid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each website will be unique, given the needs of the business. Regardless of
this, you can apply the Hierarchy of Optimization to help improve the
performance of your website and your conversions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Questions about CRO or the Hierarchy of Optimization? Want help with your &lt;a href="/consulting/"&gt;UX
design&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:3wojkp7a"&gt;Send me an email&lt;/a&gt; and let’s talk!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or still not quite sure where to spend your time and resources?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out our &lt;a href="/cro-critique/"&gt;CRO Critique&lt;/a&gt;. It’s a CRO critique of your
website that is customized to &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; business and website’s purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id='modalMaslow' class='reveal-modal' data-reveal&gt;
  &lt;h2&gt;Maslow&amp;rsquo;s Hierarchy of Needs&lt;/h2&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
    In Maslow’s Hierarchy of Needs, the most fundamental needs for human motivation
    are at the bottom. Only once these basic needs are satisfied can someone
    fulfill higher order psychological needs. (Food, water, shelter, and safety
    trump belonging, esteem, and self-actualization. But combine all of the levels
    together and you have a happy, motivated individual.)
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;a class='close-reveal-modal'&gt;&amp;#215;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Bandit Testing: When Should You Use Multi-Armed Bandit Testing</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://torspark.com/bandit-testing-when-should-you-use-multi-armed-bandit-testing/"/>
    <id>http://torspark.com/bandit-testing-when-should-you-use-multi-armed-bandit-testing/</id>
    <published>2015-02-25T08:24:00-06:00</published>
    <updated>2015-03-25T00:53:59-05:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Tania Lyerly</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Split testing. When you hear the term split testing, most people assume it is
referring to A/B testing. And typically you would be correct. However,
technically A/B testing is a type of split testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bandit testing is another type of split testing...&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Split testing. When you hear the term split testing, most people assume it is
referring to A/B testing. And typically you would be correct. However,
technically A/B testing is a type of split testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bandit testing is another type of split testing. If you’ve been doing research
into conversion rate optimization, split testing, or A/B testing, then you have
probably come across bandit testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More technically known as multi-armed bandit testing, it is an alternative
approach to split testing compared to A/B split testing. Just because bandit
testing offers a different approach does not mean you should take it. This
article will answer the following questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is multi-armed bandit testing?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How is multi-armed bandit testing different from A/B testing?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the benefits of multi-armed bandit testing?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the disadvantages to multi-armed bandit testing?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s jump right into things, shall we!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;1. What is multi-armed bandit testing?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="row of slot machines" src="/img/empty-slot-machines.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not to be confused with our raccoon friend, multi-armed bandit testing comes
from a gambling scenario. A gambler is in front of a row of slot machines (aka
one armed bandits, hence the name). The gambler knows that each machine has its
own algorithm of rewards. Some machines payout better than others. The trick is
to figure out which machines offer the better rate of return and maximize it.
The gambler will have &lt;strong&gt;two phases: explorative and exploitative&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the explorative phase the gambler will put coins into all of the
machines equally to test which gives the higher returns (aka conversions). Then
during the exploitative phase, the gambler starts to put more coins (traffic)
in the machines that have the higher rewards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;How bandit testing works with your website&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of three slot machines, we have three versions of your website (A, B,
and C). &lt;strong&gt;Our explorative and exploitative phases run indefinitely&lt;/strong&gt; (or until
we end the test).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, we can set the explorative level at 10% and the exploitative level
at 90%. (This ratio can be changed as desired). Let’s use 10,000 visitors for
an easy number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means 10% of traffic (1,000 visitors) will “explore” the variations.
Traffic is evenly distributed across all three options. The other 90% of
traffic (9,000 visitors) will be proportionally directed to the versions with
the higher conversion rates. The 90% exploits the results from the 10%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;2. How is multi-armed bandit testing different from A/B testing?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you remember from the &lt;a href="/ab-testing-crash-course-5-questions-and-answers-you-need-to-know/"&gt;A/B testing crash course
article&lt;/a&gt;,
traffic during an A/B test is split evenly between the different variations. In
our A/B/C example above, our split test would direct 33% of traffic to each
version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With A/B testing, versions that aren’t performing as well continue to receive
the same amount of traffic as the versions with a higher conversion rate. In a
bandit test, the versions with the higher conversion rates receive a higher
proportion of traffic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;3. What are the benefits of multi-armed bandit testing?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;When time is not on your side: sales or other seasonality.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is hands down &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; benefit to running a multi-armed bandit test over an
A/B test. An A/B test could run 2 weeks or even 6+ weeks long to properly
determine a winner. (A combination of statistical significance and running the
test over multiple business cycles.) Then you implement the winner on your site
for the foreseeable future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A/B tests don’t work well if you are having a sale that lasts only 3 weeks
(kind of irrelevant actually). Your goal is optimizing conversions during the
sale. A multi-armed bandit test does this. You don’t care about the foreseeable
future because there isn’t a future after the limited window of the sale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;If you are very risk averse when it comes to testing, this could be the test for you.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Honestly, I debated whether to list this as a benefit or not. Here’s why:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are very risk averse, you probably aren’t doing any kind of serious
testing. Even the best hypothesis must get tested eventually to prove its
worth. It could fail, or it could sky-rocket your conversions. You just don’t
know until you test it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, with bandit testing you get to be greedy. Traffic gets pushed to the
higher performing variations. This means you are maximizing your conversions.
&lt;em&gt;But&lt;/em&gt; this may not bode well for confidently determining the winning version.
(I’ll explain this more in the disadvantages section below.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If maximizing conversions is the name of the game, then…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Why doesn’t everyone use bandit testing instead of A/B testing?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a great question. Bandit testing has its select benefits, but it has
many disadvantages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;4. What are the disadvantages to multi-armed bandit testing?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Say it with me, &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Set it and forget!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are a lazy tester, then this is a benefit. For the rest of us, it’s a
severe disadvantage. As a serious tester, you want to determine a winner as
efficiently (and quickly) as possible. Then once you have your winner you can
run your next test. Think of it like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You test version B against your current version (A). Version B wins. Then you
test version C against B (the new original). Version B wins again. Next, you
test version D. Version D beats version B. Version D becomes the new standard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an example of the ongoing testing you should be conducting. The more
versions you test at once, the longer the test will take to determine a winner.
Which is why it is better to limit the number of versions at one time, unless
you have a &lt;em&gt;ton&lt;/em&gt; of traffic. Also, you may not have thought B would win, or
other insights came out of the test. As a result of these insights, version C
is born.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By continuously testing, you can continuously make improvements to your website
and conversion funnel.This is the only way to continue to maximize conversions,
revenue, and profit in the long term. If you “set it and forget” you aren’t
continuously improving. Instead, you are stuck in a rut and money is left on
the table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bandit tests are better used as a strategy in a specific setting rather than as
a test in the traditional A/B testing sense. Here’s why:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A bandit test can run indefinitely. It will run until the code is deleted, or
until the end of the world as we know it. Whichever happens first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is great if you want to run a test forever. It is not so great if you want
to choose and implement a winning version. Which brings me to my next several
points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;The short term conversion benefit can hurt your conversion rate in the long term.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Used in the right situation, a bandit test can be a great tool in your testing
tool belt. However, the use of bandit testing should generally be the exception
rather than the rule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the short term, your conversions are maximized. Most traffic is pushed to
the best performing version. In the long term, some percentage of traffic is
always directed towards all versions. This includes the versions not performing
as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The exploration phase never stops during a bandit test.&lt;/strong&gt; It&amp;rsquo;s part of the
code. The percentage of traffic that makes up the explorative segment can be
changed, but it never fully disappears.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In layman’s terms, the losers are always getting some traffic, unlike with an
A/B test where the winning version is eventually implemented. As a result
&lt;strong&gt;with bandit testing you lose out on a certain amount of conversions in the
long term&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe you are thinking at this point, “why can’t I have the best of both A/B
testing and bandit testing?” In theory, you run the bandit test to maximize
conversions until a winner is determined. Then delete the bandit testing code
and implement the winner. &lt;em&gt;In theory&lt;/em&gt; this works, in practicality there are
several problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Multi-armed bandit testing can take 5+ times longer to determine a winner than A/B testing.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visual Website Optimizer (VWO) ran a scenario with 3 website versions. They had
the following conversion rates: A=10%, B=15%, and C=20%. Additionally they ran
the simulation through 4 testing algorithms as denoted below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Simple randomization of A/B testing: &lt;em&gt;RAND&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multi-armed bandit (10% exploration, 90% exploitation): &lt;em&gt;MAB-10&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multi-armed bandit (50% exploration, 50% exploitation): &lt;em&gt;MAB-50&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multi-armed bandit (77% exploration, 23% exploitation): &lt;em&gt;MAB-77&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They waited for statistical significance to be found at least 10 times. These
were the results:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="iteration # when statistical significance was achieved" src="/img/vwo-bandit-vs-ab-1.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, the highest conversion rate happened with the bandit test that
had the highest exploitation. However, it took &lt;strong&gt;almost 6 times as much traffic
to declare significance&lt;/strong&gt;. This goes back to what I said above about short term
gains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the test, you optimize your conversions. But, none of the tests beat out
the 20% conversion rate of C. If you want to maximize your conversion rate long
term, you want to declare a winner as efficiently as possible. Then implement
it. In this case, version C.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;VWO ran a different simulation to test statistical significance when the
conversion rates were minimally different (10% vs 11%). The simulations were
run 25 times with 10,000 iterations.Their findings did not bode well for bandit
tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="number of times no statistical significance was seen" src="/img/vwo-bandit-vs-ab-2.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;bandit testing simulations needed more traffic to declare statistical
significance.  &lt;em&gt;And&lt;/em&gt; they were more likely not to reach statistical
significance at all&lt;/strong&gt;. Determining if a test won’t achieve statistical
significance &amp;ndash;or if there isn’t a clear conversion rate winner&amp;ndash; is crucial.
The faster that is determined, the sooner you can run a new test. Which is why
A/B testing is often the better testing choice over a multi-armed bandit test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bandit testing may inaccurately allocate traffic to variations that are actually less effective based on business cycles.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All businesses have cycles. Conversion rates often change based on daily,
weekly, and even monthly business cycles. Let’s say most of your business
during a week happens Wednesday-Friday. You start a bandit test on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on Monday and Tuesday’s conversion rates more traffic is allocated
towards version A instead of B or C. However, Monday and Tuesday are not your
&lt;em&gt;”real”&lt;/em&gt; business days. Meaning, the results from Monday and Tuesday indicating
that A is the best converter, could be a false positive of sorts. Eventually
&lt;strong&gt;the bandit test will correct itself, but the damage to lost conversions will
have been done&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bandit tests assume that time variables don’t exist. This is generally not the
case in the business world. If your business has any kind of cyclical nature to
it (most businesses do), it is better to set up an A/B test that runs over the
entire cycle. You will receive a better, more holistic view of the different
conversion rates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Users can get confused with different versions and variations.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During an A/B test, users are sorted to see the different versions or
variations via a cookie. They will always see the same version until a new (or
winning) version is implemented. This is not the case with bandit testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traffic and users are directed to the version with the highest conversion rate.
A user could see version A during an exploration phase. Then during the
exploitation phase that same user could see version B.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there is a shift in the conversion rate, or a change in the
exploration/exploitation levels, the user could be directed back to version A.
Or even to version C, if there is one. Basically, this makes for a confusing
user experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="two raccoons" src="/img/two-raccoons.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Multi-armed bandit tests are a great strategy to use when you want to
maximize conversions in a short time frame.&lt;/strong&gt; Main example of this is for
sales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally, bandit tests should not be used as an ongoing strategy for your
website. &lt;strong&gt;A/B tests are the best testing strategy to efficiently make site
choices.&lt;/strong&gt; (I.e. What version of copy goes on your sign-up button. Or what
color should the button be- green or red.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Regardless of whether you are running a multi-armed bandit test or an A/B
test, use good testing practices.&lt;/strong&gt; This means knowing the conditions for
stopping the test: length of time and statistical significance level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some testing software automatically sets a test length for 7 days and 95%
statistical significance. This does not mean those are the right conditions for
your test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that you’re armed with the knowledge of when to use multi-armed bandit
tests, feel free to implement it into your site. Just make sure you’re using it
for the right reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’d like some help setting up a custom bandit solution, check out our
&lt;a href="/consulting/"&gt;consulting options&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P.S.  For those interested in the more technical aspects of split testing &amp;mdash;
multi-armed bandit testing is a type of greedy algorithm. It can also be referred
to as an epsilon-greedy strategy. A/B split testing is considered an
epsilon-first strategy&amp;hellip; Just in case you were curious. :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P.P.S. There will be another article going into greater depth on all of these
technicalities at some point. &lt;a href="/newsletter/"&gt;Join our mailing list&lt;/a&gt; to be the
first to know about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://eegaas.deviantart.com/art/Curious-raccoon-baby-272134880"&gt;Feature image credit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Why Carousels Destroy your Conversion Rate</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://torspark.com/why-carousels-destroy-your-conversion-rate/"/>
    <id>http://torspark.com/why-carousels-destroy-your-conversion-rate/</id>
    <published>2015-02-09T22:24:00-06:00</published>
    <updated>2015-02-11T16:53:55-06:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Tania Lyerly</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Slideshows, carousels, and rotating offers. Three names for the same thing:
conversion killer!  A lot of homepages have carousels. Marketers and clients of
designers love them because carousels look cool. They let you get a lot more
information on...&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Slideshows, carousels, and rotating offers. Three names for the same thing:
conversion killer!  A lot of homepages have carousels. Marketers and clients of
designers love them because carousels look cool. They let you get a lot more
information on your homepage, and you don’t have to decide which is most
important. If carousels are so cool and popular, why do &lt;strong&gt;your sales funnel and
bottom line hate carousels&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Key Reasons Why Carousels Kill Your Conversion Rate&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Low user engagement&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Low click-through rate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Positioning overrules great content&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Usability sucks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Banner blindness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Carousels have low levels of user engagement and click-through rates&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes carousels look pretty, but people don’t engage with them. Don’t believe me?
Erik Runyon proved it. (He’s the Director of Web Communications at the
University of Notre Dame. He’s also a web developer.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Erik tracked user engagement of carousels on four of Notre Dame’s websites. His
findings: &lt;strong&gt;1% of visitors clicked on the carousel&lt;/strong&gt;. To put that in
perspective, if you have 100,000 visitors to your website, only 1,000 will click
on the carousel. And there’s more!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking a closer look at the features in positions 2-5 in the carousels, they
range from approximately 3% in position 2 to 2.6% in position 5. &lt;strong&gt;Less than 3%
of 1% of visitors clicked through a carousel.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="ND.edu Feature Click-through Rates
graph" src="/img/ndedu-carousel-click-through-rates.png" /&gt;
&lt;a href="http://erikrunyon.com/2013/07/carousel-interaction-stats/"&gt;image credit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you had 100,000 visitors that 3% of 1% represents ONLY 30 visitors. That’s a
pretty terrible click-through rate! Instead what matters is the position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Position 1 Has the Highest Conversions, but You May Be Leaving Conversions on the Table&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe you’re thinking, “What if we rotate what is in the first position? Then we
don’t have to worry about click-through rates.” From a usability stand-point,
this is an awful idea (more explanation on that in a bit). Erik tracked this
too. Here’s what he found (site 4 in red is the auto-rotate).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Feature Click-through Rates Multiple Sites
graph" src="/img/ndedu-carousel-click-through-rates-sites.png" /&gt;
&lt;a href="http://erikrunyon.com/2013/01/carousel-stats/"&gt;image credit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, whatever is shown in &lt;strong&gt;position one always has the highest conversion
rate regardless of the message&lt;/strong&gt;. The reason is position one receives the most
traffic views and interaction (being first and all that). If the message in
position one is not your most compelling message, then you are losing out on
conversions and revenue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="/catalyst/"&gt;A/B testing&lt;/a&gt; can help you determine your best message&lt;/strong&gt; so you
don&amp;rsquo;t leave conversions and money on the table.  Here’s an example of how A/B
testing could improve your conversion rate (or carousel, though we generally
recommend not using carousels in the first place):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say you sell watches. You have three watches that are the same except for
color: silver, blue, and black. You decide to have a carousel that shows each of
the three watches in that order (silver, blue, and black).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know from Erik’s study that the silver watch will receive the most traffic
engagement. It will appear to have the highest conversion rate because of its
position. However, had you A/B tested each of the watches individually your
conversion rates change. For the sake of the example, say you found that the
silver watch had a conversion rate of 10%, the blue 5%, and the black 20%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meaning the black watch, if it was in position 1, would double your conversions.
Instead, the black watch is barely generating you any conversions hidden away in
position 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The top of your homepage is prime real estate! You should have one focused
message that maximizes visitor engagement. (If you aren’t sure on the best
message, A/B test it.) The last thing you want to do is frustrate your visitors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Carousels Frustrate and Annoy Visitors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Guy punching laptop" src="/img/guy-punching-laptop.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usability for carousels sucks!  And auto-rotating carousels are the worst of the
worst. Here’s why:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some carousels auto-rotate and there is no navigation options for the user.
Meaning if your visitor sees something they like and misses it, they have to
wait through the whole slideshow again. Seriously?!? Who wants to do that? I’ll
tell you who, nobody.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Visitors are less likely to generate a conversion when frustrated or
annoyed.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, what if your user misses the content that was relevant to them? They may
not even realize they missed something. The Neilsen Norman Group did a usability
study on auto-forwarding carousels. They found that the user was given the task:
&lt;em&gt;“Does Siemens have any special deals on washing machines?”&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;The user failed
the task to find the needed information because the panel auto-rotated&lt;/strong&gt; instead
of staying still.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, even if you give your visitors navigation controls, everyone reads at
different speeds. It’s annoying to have content change when you are in the
middle of reading it. Or you have to wait for it to change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As discussed previously, carousels that don’t auto-rotate will depend on
position strength to generate conversions. This is of course assuming your
visitors aren’t ignoring your carousel in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Visitors are Ignoring Your Carousel ON PURPOSE!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s called banner blindness. Consciously or subconsciously visitors are
ignoring your carousels because they are mistaking them for an advertisement.
(They look like banners.) Remember Erik Runyon’s research? 99% of visitors were
NOT interacting with the carousel. Some visitors may have not found the content
relevant, but a large number were probably just ignoring the carousel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider this statistic from Solve Media (an advertising consulting company):
you are 475.28 times more likely to survive a plane crash than you are to click
on a banner ad. Meaning, if your visitors consciously or subconsciously think
your carousel is an ad, it is going to get ignored. &lt;strong&gt;Your most important
content is being ignored because it is in a carousel.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Alternatives to using a Carousel&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point we are in agreement: carousels look cool but kill your conversion
rate. So what other options do you have?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kill the carousel and replace it with &lt;strong&gt;one main, focused message&lt;/strong&gt;. If you
aren’t sure which your best message is, A/B test it. (&lt;a href="/catalyst/"&gt;We can help you with
that&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another option is to &lt;strong&gt;replace the carousel with a user self-identified
persona&lt;/strong&gt; like vitamintalent.com does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Sceenshot of vitamintalent.com" src="/img/vitamin-talent-screenshot.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clicking “Hire Talent” vs “Looking for work?” directs the user to the most
relevant part of the site for them. (Also notice the singular focused message!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on your business, &lt;strong&gt;replace the carousel with a video&lt;/strong&gt;. It could be
demoing a product or a relevant how-to video. Video content is a great addition
to your site to help improve conversions. As an added bonus, video content will
help your SEO rankings! Google ranks websites with video content higher than
those without.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could also &lt;strong&gt;replace the carousel with a call-to-action or sign-up form&lt;/strong&gt;.
No place on your website is more visible than the top of your homepage. It is
prime real-estate. A strong call-to-action or sign-up form here that resonates
with your visitors can give your conversion rate a healthy boost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;If You Must Use a Carousel…&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are times when a carousel is useful. But you should be careful when,
where, and how they are used. Portfolios, a gallery of photographs, or any
product that is very visually oriented are perfect examples. (Think about the
real-estate industry or fashion/jewelry industries.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Carousels should appear below the fold and contain non-vital content.&lt;/strong&gt; You
should not rely on a carousel as the primary delivery option for your most
important content. Instead the carousel should complement your homepage content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make the carousel navigation obvious and 100% user controlled.&lt;/strong&gt; Slower and
international readers will thank you. In fact all of your visitors will thank
you for returning the power to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use no more than 3-4 slides on your carousel.&lt;/strong&gt; The click-through rate is very
low at this point. The chances of slides in position four and later being viewed
are diminutive. (Really, the chances of slides after position one being viewed
at all are small.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a select few circumstances, a carousel can be a beneficial addition to your
homepage or website. However, most businesses don’t fall under those
circumstances. Instead, their carousels are killing their conversions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your site has a carousel, send whoever needs convincing a &lt;a href="/why-carousels-destroy-your-conversion-rate/"&gt;link to this
page&lt;/a&gt; before that carousel kills
any more of your conversions.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A/B Testing Crash Course: 5 Questions (and Answers) You Need to Know</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://torspark.com/ab-testing-crash-course-5-questions-and-answers-you-need-to-know/"/>
    <id>http://torspark.com/ab-testing-crash-course-5-questions-and-answers-you-need-to-know/</id>
    <published>2015-02-02T22:04:00-06:00</published>
    <updated>2015-02-11T15:04:28-06:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Tania Lyerly</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No Textbook required. Not even a Dictionary.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here at Torspark, we are firm believers in asking lots of questions. With that
in mind, here are the most common questions about A/B testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is A/B testing?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What can A/B testing do for your business...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No Textbook required. Not even a Dictionary.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here at Torspark, we are firm believers in asking lots of questions. With that
in mind, here are the most common questions about A/B testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is A/B testing?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What can A/B testing do for your business?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How does A/B testing work?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do you pick the winner of an A/B test?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How long should you run an A/B test?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bonus Question: What do all of those marketing sales-y speak headlines &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt;
mean?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A straightforward bundle of questions to ask, but the &lt;strong&gt;answers are a different
matter&lt;/strong&gt;. The answers tend to be made more complicated than they should be from a
combination of technical terms and sales-y marketing speak. This is why we
decided to answer these questions, minus the dictionary, textbook, or marketing
translator to understand. Here we go!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;1. What is A/B testing?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A/B testing (or split testing) is when you &lt;strong&gt;test two variations&lt;/strong&gt; of something to
see &lt;strong&gt;which performs better&lt;/strong&gt;. Usually you test a new version (B) that you think
could do better against the control version (A). Or if you don’t have a control
version, you could just start testing both alternatives against each other right
away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can test more than two variations as well. A three variation split test
would be known as an A/B/C test. One letter is assigned for each variation, and
you could continue on with four or more variations in this manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;2. What can A/B testing do for your business?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The primary use for A/B testing is to &lt;strong&gt;gather conversion data&lt;/strong&gt;. To understand the
importance of conversion data, let’s talk about data and sales funnels for a
second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have enough data, you can construct the flow of your sales funnel. This
means determining where your traffic is coming from, how many people are
clicking through your website, how many people end up &lt;strong&gt;buying your product&lt;/strong&gt; or
service, and what path they took to get there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, even the best sales funnels leak. Holes in your funnel are &lt;strong&gt;where people
drop off&lt;/strong&gt; at each stage. By seeing the big picture painted by the data, you can
figure out where the leaks are. Once you know where the barriers to conversion
are, you can start to fix them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fix can be anything from better headlines and copy to adding (or removing)
videos. Sometimes it’s even as simple as changing the color of a button. It
really just &lt;strong&gt;depends on your customers&lt;/strong&gt; and what they respond to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where A/B testing comes into play. It is used to test those fixes to
your leaking sales funnel. By A/B testing the fix, you can determine if your fix
&lt;strong&gt;actually works&lt;/strong&gt;. Or if your fix made your sales funnel leak some more. Or if it
didn’t make a difference either way. Some fixes will have a greater improvement
than others, while sometimes you will need a combination of fixes to see an
improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With some trial and error, you can &lt;strong&gt;find the right combination to optimize
conversions&lt;/strong&gt; and minimize leaks in your sales funnel. The right boost to your
conversion rate should &lt;strong&gt;increase your revenue&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you understand the theory for A/B testing, but what does this look like with
some real numbers? Don&amp;rsquo;t worry, you won&amp;rsquo;t need a calculator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Scientific Calculator and Stats Book" src="/img/scientific-calculator.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say you have a business selling some software. Your current conversion
rate is 10%, and your yearly revenue is $500,000. Your business then conducts
several A/B tests to optimize conversions in your sales funnel (without changing
prices). As a result, you were able to increase your total overall conversion
rate by 3%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You new total conversion rate is now 13% (10% original + 3% improvement = 13%).
That extra 3% increase in your total conversion rate represents an additional
$15,000 in &lt;strong&gt;yearly revenue&lt;/strong&gt; for your business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not a bad chunk of change for running a few tests. Especially when you consider
that your business will get this extra $15,000 &lt;em&gt;every year&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if your business was able to continue to optimize your conversions
overtime? So that 3% increase became 5% or 7% as different tests improved
different aspects of your sales funnel. Those percentages will compound (just
like compounding interest rates), and revenue will really increase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;3. How does A/B testing work?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say you want to target the number of people signing up for a free demo on
your website. You are worried you are missing out on conversions because you
think people &lt;em&gt;aren’t noticing&lt;/em&gt; the bland button that blends into the background.
You decide to perform an A/B test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="A/B testing gray button vs orange button" src="/img/ab-test-gray-orange-button.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original button is version “A” and the new bright orange button is version
“B”. Half of your traffic to the website will see version “A” and half will see
version “B”. Some tools will declare the winning version based on the higher
conversion rate after a set amount of time or visitors. They’ll even
automatically apply the changes as soon as they pick a winner. This &lt;strong&gt;is not&lt;/strong&gt; how
you want to declare a test winner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;4. How do you pick the winner of an A/B test?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Excited Kids with Laptop" src="/img/excited-kids.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Declaring a winner sounds simple, but it can get a little tricky because of the
multiple factors: sample size, statistical significance, and getting an &lt;strong&gt;accurate
representation of your business traffic&lt;/strong&gt;. (Wait, don’t grab your textbook yet!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statistical significance is when a statistic is deemed reliable. So a test with
a 95% statistical significance means there is &lt;strong&gt;less than a 5% chance&lt;/strong&gt; that the
results of the test could be due to &lt;em&gt;random chance&lt;/em&gt;. Remember, the higher the
statistical significance percentage, the more you can trust in the results of
your test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To achieve a higher level of statistical significance, you will need to increase
your sample size (the number of people you are testing). You will also need to
increase your sample size the more variations you test. In all honesty, your
sample size can &lt;em&gt;never be too big&lt;/em&gt;. This is where time and money become factors,
which we’ll explore in the next section. But you will need certain minimums to
achieve statistical significance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sample size and statistical significance alone are &lt;strong&gt;not enough&lt;/strong&gt; to declare a
winner when making business decisions. Your test should run long enough for your
sample size to &lt;strong&gt;accurately represent&lt;/strong&gt; your business traffic. These elements
combined together help you decide how long to run the test for and eventually
for declaring the winner and &lt;strong&gt;making the right decision&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;5. How long should you run an A/B test?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The very simple statistical answer is once a test has reached statistical
significance then the test is complete, but that isn’t entirely accurate when
&lt;strong&gt;trying to make an informed decision&lt;/strong&gt;. It is at best a half answer and very
misleading at worst. You want to achieve a combination of a high level of
statistical significance that is indicative of your conversion funnel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider this&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if you get all of the traffic you need for statistical significance in an
hour? Is that one hour’s worth of traffic truly representative of all your
business traffic? Maybe yes… maybe no… But the only way you can be certain is to
let the test continue to run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you declare a winner that is statistically significant but is &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt;
representative of your business traffic, you could be implementing a change that
actually hurts your business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going back to our version “A” gray button and version “B” orange button, let’s
say version “A” reaches statistical significance in one hour. If you peek at the
results early, you may see “A” as being the winner. However, if you let the test
continue to run, you’d end up with version “B” having a higher conversion rate
in the longer term with a larger sample size. In this scenario, the traffic in
the one hour was &lt;strong&gt;not indicative&lt;/strong&gt; of the larger conversion funnel trend where
version “B” was the true winner. This is why you shouldn&amp;rsquo;t peek at ongoing
tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This gets us back to the original question of how long to run a test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We recommend that A/B tests should be run through &lt;strong&gt;a minimum of two online
business cycles&lt;/strong&gt;. This helps to minimize the chance of anomalies and false
positives in the data. In theory, the data that comes from those two business
cycles should look pretty similar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How long is your online business cycle? An online business cycle usually ranges
from &lt;strong&gt;one to four weeks&lt;/strong&gt;, but will vary from business to business. It depends on
your consistent activities for &lt;strong&gt;driving traffic&lt;/strong&gt; to your business, but we’ll dive
into that another time. (If you’d like help figuring out your online business
cycle, just &lt;a href="mailto:3wojkp7a"&gt;shoot us an email&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you make the front page of a major site like &lt;a href="http://techcrunch.com"&gt;Tech
Crunch&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.reddit.com"&gt;reddit&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/"&gt;Hacker
News&lt;/a&gt; and get an &lt;em&gt;abnormal&lt;/em&gt; spike in traffic during
one cycle, be cautious when making any decisions. Ask yourself if that traffic
really represents your usual business. You should consider running the test even
longer to balance things out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this ladies and gentlemen is how a statistical answer to a business scenario
can be both correct &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; incorrect at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you have a basic understanding of A/B testing. So let’s spice things up a
little bit and get fancy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;6. Bonus Question: What do all of those marketing sales-y speak headlines &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; mean?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You think you have a handle on this A/B testing thing and then you come across a
headline like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&amp;ldquo;We’ll &lt;strong&gt;increase your conversions&lt;/strong&gt; by 30%!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Fancy Marketer&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That sounds great. Where do I sign up?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have probably seen similar sales-y headlines elsewhere. Maybe you are
thinking about that 3% increase in conversion rate earlier. The headline says
30%. Done!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;….&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wait a second… Take a closer look at that headline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It says “increase your conversions &lt;em&gt;by&lt;/em&gt;” a certain percentage.  Why is this one
word such a big deal?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time to break down the sales and marketing speak and understand what those
numbers &lt;em&gt;truly&lt;/em&gt; mean. Because the numbers &lt;em&gt;sound&lt;/em&gt; great, but they may not mean
what you think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Example:
Let’s again say you’re selling some software and your current conversion rate is
10%. We’ll go big with a 30% increase, improvement, or 
&lt;span data-tooltip aria-haspopup="true" class="has-tip" title="more fancy marketing speak"&gt;lift&lt;/span&gt;
on that original 10%. This actually means a &lt;em&gt;true&lt;/em&gt; 3% increase to your original
conversion rate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s &lt;strong&gt;how it works&lt;/strong&gt;. The 30% is applied to the 10% conversion rate, NOT the
total overall conversion rate. 30% of 10% is 3%. (Here’s how the math works
(.3) * (.1) = .03 or 3%.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In layman’s terms, a 30% increase means your old conversion rate of 10% is now
13%. Huh… that 30% seems a little misleading now, doesn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before you get too disappointed, as discussed before, a 3% increase to your
total conversion rate can be a huge &lt;strong&gt;boost to your revenue&lt;/strong&gt;. The best part is as
long as you have the traffic, your testing options to &lt;strong&gt;optimize your sales funnel&lt;/strong&gt;
are endless! The more leaks you patch and barriers you remove to conversions in
your sales funnel, the more you will increase your revenue. A/B testing can
help get you there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: you also need to remember that a 3% improvement in your conversion rate
doesn’t help much if you had to cut your prices in half to get it… But, that’s
for another article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frankly, we love using A/B testing to optimize conversion funnels. Why? Because
&lt;strong&gt;little changes&lt;/strong&gt; can have &lt;strong&gt;big results&lt;/strong&gt;, big changes can have even bigger results,
and they all compound together!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;What’s your next step? What are you going to test? We’d love to &lt;a href="mailto:3wojkp7a"&gt;hear about it&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have a question about what you just read, a question about something else
related to A/B testing, or just want to say hello? &lt;a href="mailto:3wojkp7a"&gt;Shoot us an email&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
